<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The praise of a good name The reproch of an ill name. Wherin euery one may see the fame that followeth laudable actions, and the infamy that cometh by the contrary. With certaine pithy apothegues, very profitable for this age, by C.G.</title>
            <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01682</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849118</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849118</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14253</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01682)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14253)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 709:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The praise of a good name The reproch of an ill name. Wherin euery one may see the fame that followeth laudable actions, and the infamy that cometh by the contrary. With certaine pithy apothegues, very profitable for this age, by C.G.</title>
                  <author>Gibbon, Charles, fl. 1589-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 55, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Iohn Windet, for Thomas Gosson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.G. = Charles Gibbon.</note>
                  <note>Some leaves cropped at head, affecting running title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PRAISE of a good Name The reproch of an ill Name. Wherin euery one may see the fame that followeth laudable actions, and the infamy that cometh by the contrary. With certaine pithy apothegues, very profitable for this age, by C.G.</p>
            <p>London: Imprinted by Iohn Windet, for Thomas Gosson, 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:2"/>
            <head>To ſome of the beſt and moſt ciuill ſort of the Inhabitants of S. Edmonds Bury. <hi>Char. Gibbon wiſheth all proſperous ſucceſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>CIPIO</hi> hauing a great ſumme of money ſent him from a mighty and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificall perſon, ſaide, hee had rather hee could rule him that gaue it, then receiue his gift: his ingratefull acceptance of ſo great a preſent, had almoſt diſmaide me to offer a peece of paper, but that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume of you, as neighbours.</p>
            <p>That diuine <hi>Plato</hi> ſaith, a man is not borne for his owne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite onely, but for others: and <hi>S. Peter</hi> willeth e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery one to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the gift, as he hath receiued to others: I hope therefore you will not miſlike him that doth manifeſt his good mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing vnto you, but weigh a well-willer by his mind, as the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s by her myte.</p>
            <p>There are many like the floud <hi>Tagus</hi> in <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> which carry a ſhow without ſubſtance, as that doth a grauell like gold, &amp; yet are ſo ſelfe-conceited, that they contemne all other: whoſe iudgements if they come to be tried in deede, are as farre from ſence, as the blind man was from ſight, when he could not diſcerne men from trees. <hi>Mark. 8.4.</hi> A man to perceiue he is ignorant (ſaith <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dymus</hi>) is a token of wiſedome: then what ſhall we eſtimate theſe who thinke none wiſe but themſelues, the more learned a man be, the more lowly he ſhould beare himſelfe ſaith <hi>Cicero,</hi> they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:14253:3"/> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> well to remember <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, no man may profite ſo much in hearing, but while he liueth, he ſhall haue neede to be taught.</p>
            <p>There bee ſome that ſtand altogether vppon Academicall tearmes, who accompt no writers good but graduates: As all men ought to reuerence ſchooles of learning, ſo no ſcholler is to haue honor for his degrees, but his learning. Yet we muſt not all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes tie Gods giftes, to meanes: for hee woorketh, when, where, and how he pleaſeth. To cenſure men by outward circumſtances, when their actions are ſincere: or to thincke the worſe of their attemptes, becauſe they want fronted titles, are ieſtes fit for Iewes: for when they could find no fault at <hi>Chriſts</hi> doctrine, they ſought to impaire it, by his birth and bringing vp: <hi>Whence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth this wiſedome and great workes, is not this the Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſonne. Matth. 13.54.</hi> A poore craftes-man inſtructed <hi>Apollos,</hi> a very mighty and eloquent man. <hi>Act. 18.27.</hi> Yet hee diſdained not his counſell by his crafte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith truely, <hi>Omnes eos contemnunt, de quibus male exiſtimant.</hi> Let a worke be neuer ſo perfect, a mans enemy will depraue it, he that enuies the Actor, will neuer aduaunce his action, be it neuer ſo vertuous: ſuch men as theſe, are not to be medled with: for as <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, they are ſooner van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed with ſilence, then with aunſweares: for malice is ſooner ſtirred, then ſtaid with wordes: and as for malice, it drinkes the moſt part of his owne poyſon, and therefore the Philoſopher proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the venome of a malitious man to be woorſe, then of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: for the venome that ſerpents haue, for the deſtruction of men, they keepe it without their owne perill: but malice, hurteth him moſt that doth retaine it.</p>
            <p>There be others that like the Iewes, value mens woorkes by their weaknes, as they did the blind-mans ſayinges by his ſight:
<pb facs="tcp:14253:3"/> 
               <hi>Thou art altogether bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>anes, doeſt thou teach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iohn. 9.34. S. Gregory</hi> ſaith well, God ſpareth ſome heere t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> torment afterward, others he doth puniſh, which hee will after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpare: If thou haſt not taſted of troubles, I ſay as <hi>Seneca</hi> did, I iudge thee to be miſerable, that neuer kneweſt miſery. It is good for a man (ſaith <hi>Ieremy</hi>) to beare the yoake in his youth. <hi>Lament. 3.</hi> Yet there is no reaſon that any common impediments ſhould impaire a credible action: for who wil thinke the woorſe of a pretious ſtone, becauſe it is taken from an infectious toade, or of a bullion of gold, becauſe it is digged out of the filthy ground, or of <hi>Salomons</hi> workes becauſe he was giuen to wantonneſſe.</p>
            <p>There be others that take no pleaſure, but in ploddi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for earthly mucke, who eſteeme learning to bee madneſſe as <hi>Fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> did <hi>Act. 26.</hi> it makes me remember a prety merryment of a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-man, who looking vpon an Ape in a Dutch-mans ſhop, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s mockt and mowed at, inſomuch as he rebuked the Ape, and ſad his parentes had well brought him vp: one which ſtood by, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d him it was no child but an Ape, good Lord (ſaith he) what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thinges the Dutch-folkes can make for money: theſe cynic a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, are like the countreyman: for I haue heard ſome of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of good bookes, as he did by the Ape, what toyes and deuiſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inuented for money, and in deede, doe repute them to be nothin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> els, but the practiſes of idle wittes, theſe dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dges do eſteeme more of a penny, then a good booke, as <hi>Eſops</hi> cocke did of a barley corne, better then a pearle, and therefore may bee fitly reſembled to the Poets fiction: for their deſires like <hi>Danaae,</hi> will bee pleaſed with nothing but a ſhower of gold.</p>
            <p>There is an other ſort of people that liue like wenills by the malt, all vpon the ſpoyle, as delighting in nothing els, but ſuch things as be incident to theſe common hackſters. Vaine ſpending, ill ſpeaking, idle liuing, vnlawfull gaming, with whome a good
<pb facs="tcp:14253:4"/> action is as much ſet by as a ſheepekeeper amongſt the Egyptians. <hi>Gen. 46.34.</hi> If the <hi>Romanes</hi> would puniſh ſuch as went in the ſtreetes without a badge of their occupation, how are they to bee delt with that haue no faculties or honeſt trades to take to? If the Statute for vagabonds made in ann. 14. <hi>Eliz.</hi> were well looked to, many of theſe would come within the compaſſe of it: for they can hardly giue accompt of their liuing.</p>
            <p>There be others that like <hi>Hanun,</hi> are ready to croſſe a man with vnkindneſſe for a good turne, as he did <hi>Dauid</hi> with diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie for his good-will. Ingratitude in theſe dayes is as common as a diſh of ſnailes amongſt the Grecians, therefore true is that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Tacitus,</hi> an ill turne is ſooner requited then a good: for thancke is reputed a charge, but reuengement an aduauntage. There be few ſuch as <hi>Eliſha</hi> liuing: for when hee had receyued kindneſſe of the <hi>Shunanimite,</hi> he could not reſt till he had requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it. <hi>2. King. 4.</hi> very ſenſible is that ſaying of <hi>Seneca,</hi> a good man doth all thinges well, if hee doth all well, hee cannot bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knd: it is a diſhoneſt perſon (ſaith <hi>Plautus</hi>) that knowes how to take a benefite, and not how to requite it; Is there any man that carries ſuch a minde (ſaith <hi>Tully</hi>) that he will be vnmindfull of a good turne? For this cauſe the heathen men made a law to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the vnthankefull perſons with death, it was ſo odious in all ages.</p>
            <p>Neighbours and friendes, I goe not about to beard any man (eſpecially ſuch as be ciuill) for I am of this minde, he that offers me the leaſt pleaſure, ſhall find me ready to requite it, if diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure without cauſe, <hi>ego illum flocci pendo.</hi> Haue you not ſuch amongſt you, as make a comment of mens credites, that maligne thoſe that carry not their mindes, that ieſt and iere at others mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, that will talke what they pleaſe without controlement, that are of no accompt, and yet are countenanced. Are there not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:14253:4"/> whiſperers and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, that goe betweene the barke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tree, which doe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and exaſperate great men to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all eſtimation an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eing from good men, &amp; make but a ſport of it, and yet <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſaith, he that diminiſheth the loue in a mans hart from his neighbour, more offendeth then he that puls the meat out of the mouth of a hungry beggar: for like as the ſoul is more pretious then the body, ſo is the food of the ſoule of more eſtimation then the nouriſhment of carraine.</p>
            <p>What greater griefe can be to the godly then to ſee abiectes to inſult, and be moſt ſet by, or bad fellowes to be ſecrete informers and yet borne with: dwell not (ſaith Plato) where ſuperfluous expences doe ſurmount thy reuenues, nor where ill men be more made on then good men. Was there any thing more afflicted <hi>Dauids</hi> minde then to behold the fauour and flouriſhing eſtate of the wicked more then others? I can ſpeake ſomewhat by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, the time was, when one being perſecuted amongſt you (as the beſt that feare God may fall) it was a world to ſee how the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of the wicked wrought? diſgrace him what y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> can, ſaith one, driue him out of towne ſaith another, with many ſuch impudent ſpeeches, as ought not once to be conceiued amongſt Chriſtians: for as one of the fathers ſaith, that which is ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to vtter, is ſo to thincke: if the ſeely worme will turne ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich is trode on, what cauſe hath this to ſpeake that was thus ſpited.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the Empero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earing that an old woman was ill intreated of one of his ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ours, he diſcharged him out of his ſeruice, and gaue him in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dage vnto the woman, that by his craft being a carpenter, he might get her liuing for amends: if all were ſo ſerued that deſerue it woorſe then the ſouldior, there would be leſſe emulation, and better communication amongſt men. But as <hi>Cato,</hi> inueighing againſt lewd people, ſaid, it was in vaine to talke to a belly that lacketh eares, ſo it is friuolous to
<pb facs="tcp:14253:5"/> infourme theſe, whoſe tounges are like the poyſon of aſpes, whoſe eares are as deafe as the adders, whoſe hartes are leſſe pittyfull then Iewes. Yet this I will ſay, I neuer knew any man vnkind and cruell to another, that hath not bene met with the like in his life time, <hi>vt ſementem feceris ita &amp; metes. Boetius</hi> reportes that one <hi>Buſyris</hi> a giant, did alwayes vſe to kill his geſtes: <hi>Hercules</hi> lodging in his houſe as a gueſt afterward killed him, little did <hi>Manaſſes</hi> thincke to haue bene fettered in iron chaines, when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> afflicted many good men, or <hi>Paul</hi> to haue bene whipt and impr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned, when he perſecuted the Saintes, or <hi>Sampſon</hi> to haue bene a laughing-ſtocke, when he was in full ſtrength: therfore no man knowes what hangs ouer his owne head, but that he or his may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come one day a pray or a prouerbe to his enemies, aſwell as others.</p>
            <p>There is no gardeine that hath flowers, but hath weedes: nor any place that hath good-men, but hath bad, there was one tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor among the twelue Apoſtles: there was <hi>Cham</hi> aſwell as <hi>Sem</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke. If tenne righteous men could not be found in <hi>Sodom,</hi> which was a great Citie, you muſt not thincke much though there be ſome lewde people in <hi>Bury</hi> which is but a towne: Theſe and ſuch as theſe, I vtterly exempt out of this dedication, but for the beſt and moſt ciuile ſort, as I were loth any way to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, ſo I thought good to beſtow this treatiſe vpon them in teſtimony thereof; deſiring nothing but a frendly acceptance for my paynes, and a good-word in recompence for my good-will. So not omitting any neceſſary duety I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to the tuition of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are no greater enemies to any forward enterpriſe then <hi>Enuy</hi> and <hi>Ignorance:</hi> for as one of malice will not ſo the other of ſimpleneſſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, geue learning her due. If ſuch as theſe ſhoote their boltes at my booke, I ſhall weigh their words as <hi>Seneca</hi> did, when he was rayled on by the like: I haue no reaſon (ſaith he) to be moued with thoſe, which haue their mindes tainted with malice, their mouthes vnbrid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> modeſtie, their heads vnripened in iudgement, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lelius, Scipio,</hi> (laudable and learned men) ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o report, then I had iuſt cauſe to complaine. Such as be publike wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters them ſelues, will ſpeake well, others, if they bee wiſe, will wiſh well, my deſire is to pleaſe the better ſort, as for the reſt I reſpect not: whether it bee for ſcornefulneſſe to voutchſafe reading, or for ſparingneſſe to ſaue money, or for idleneſſe to beſtow time, there was neuer ſo many bookes among ſo few Readers: for my part I am indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, if my labours be ouerlooked, they will imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rt my good meaning, if they be not, they ſhall miniſter leſſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliking. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:6"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame.
<list>
                     <item>Is ſet foorth by the ſingularitie: for it is more excellent then
<list>
                           <item>Any riches. <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.1.</item>
                           <item>Precious ointments. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.3.</item>
                           <item>Length of dayes. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 41.13.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Conſiſteth in learned and laudable actions. included or compaſſed by
<list>
                           <item>Dexteritie</item>
                           <item>Actiuitie</item>
                           <item>Integritie</item>
                           <item>Abilitie</item>
                        </list> or ſuch like.</item>
                     <item>Muſt bée had in great regard for
<list>
                           <item>the effectes that follow: it maketh
<list>
                                 <item>the Name renowned</item>
                                 <item>the Memoriall bleſſed</item>
                              </list> 
                              <hi>Pro.</hi> 10.</item>
                           <item>the preuenting of infamy and impiety that procure it. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.37.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>May be ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed by
<list>
                           <item>Many preſumptions of euill and yet innocent. <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.12.</item>
                           <item>Meanes of flanderous and malicious reportes. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 6.13.</item>
                           <item>Occaſion of ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>minious and notorious crimes and actes.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14253:6"/>
            <head>The Praiſe of a good Name.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very one by nature is deſirous of a Name, and ſo deſirous, that many ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they will haue it buried in obliuion, will pretermit no practiſes be they neuer ſo impious to procure it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Heathen Hiſtories it is reported of one that burnt the Capitoll of <hi>Rome,</hi> who béeing dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nded why hée did ſo? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>unſweared, becauſe he would be ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>In the diuine Scriptures it is recorded, that <hi>Nimrod</hi> and hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ompany enterpriſed that preſumptuous bui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>g of <hi>Babel</hi> to no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther end, but that they might get them a Name. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.4.</p>
            <p>The practiſe of <hi>Polygamy,</hi> was vſed of many of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fore-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers, that they might haue a large poſterity, no doubt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Names.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Daughters</hi> of <hi>Lot,</hi> were loath their fathers Na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eriſh: this was one cauſe to procure that inceſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erue his ſeede. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The memoriall of Names, hath of antiquitie beene had in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch reuerent eſtimation, that our Aunceſters prouided poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>call Lawes to preſerue their Names.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the old Law, none <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to a ſtranger, but to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f his own ſtocke, to no other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but to preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue their Names. <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. For this cauſe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Boar,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of great wealth, take <hi>Ruth</hi> a poore woman to his wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> hée was her next kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. And for this cauſe was <hi>Onan</hi> cut off, becauſe he would not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oo the office of a kinſman to <hi>Tamar</hi> after his brothers death. <hi>Gen.</hi> 38.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14253:7"/>
            <p>By the ſame Law, none might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Inheritance but to ſome of hys kindred, becauſe it might ſtir vp the Name of the dead, <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4.5. It was this that made <hi>Naomi</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi> come out of <hi>Bethelem,</hi> becauſe they might not ſell their parcell of land to a ſtraunger: and for this cauſe was <hi>Naboth</hi> vnwilling to part from his Vineyard (though it was requeſted by a king) becauſe it was his Inheritance 1. <hi>King.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So common a principle of experience hath it beene in all ages, and amongſt all eſtates, that rather then they would haue their Names extinct, they omitted nothing that might be a meane to maintaine them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Romaines (as <hi>Boetius</hi> maketh mention) had a Table of braſſe, in which the Names of famous and noble men were vſed to be written for a perpetuall fame or memory, and if any of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward were conuicted off fellony, or any egregious offence, hée was preſently ſtrooke out of the Table, and that was called the death of preſcription.</p>
            <p>Some for want of iſſue, builde glorious habitations, and call their Landes by their Names. The Pſalmiſt obſerued, that in his time. <hi>pſal.</hi> 49.11. <hi>Abſolom</hi> erected a pillar and called it by his owne <hi>Name,</hi> becauſe he had no ſonne to kéepe it in remembrance, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.18.</p>
            <p>Some build or buy whole Citties and Townes, and call them by their Names. The Iſraelites did ſo. 1. <hi>Chro.</hi> 6.65. or by their childrens Names as <hi>Caine</hi> did, who built a Citty and called it by his ſonnes Name, becauſe his vile act was an vtter coinquination of his owne Name. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.17.</p>
            <p>What excéeding ioy was there at the birth of <hi>Obed,</hi> the text ſaith, becauſe the Name of the dead ſhould bee continued in Iſraell. <hi>Ruth.</hi> 4.14. héereof many are de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rous of children, becauſe by their ofſpring their Names are after a ſort reduced from death.</p>
            <p>Many Monarches, Kinges, Princes, and perſons of renowne, haue ſumptuous Sepulchers, and coſtly Tombes vppon their graues, <hi>pro memoria mortuorum:</hi> not ſo much for the royalty of their eſtates, as for a remembraunce of their Names. <hi>Iaacob</hi> ſet vp a pillar vppon his wiues graue, and it is called the pillar of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14253:7"/> 
               <hi>Rahels</hi> graue to this day.</p>
            <p>There be others that haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>phes and Epigrams eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon their Graue-ſtones, for no other cauſe, but that theyr Names might be remembred when they are read.</p>
            <p>Then ſéeing there is none but is deſirous of a Name, how bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is hée aboue other, that deſerues a good Name: for <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>the memoriall of the iuſt ſhalbe bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A good Name is to be accounted a great bleſſing: for God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to the godly, that he will exalt them in Prayſe, in Name, and in Glory. <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.19. Amongſt many other bleſſings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Lord ſaide, hee would make his Name great. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.2.</p>
            <p>A good Name, <hi>poſt funera viuit,</hi> it doth not onely reuiue the dead, but reioyce the liuing by remembring, it addeth a comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the deceaſed, and a conſolation to his ſucceſſors: <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith, if a man lead a good and honeſt l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, it is profitable to himſelfe, but a good Name or report is profitable to others: For there is nothing more excellent of an earthly bleſſing, then a good Name.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good Name is better then Riches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat more eſtimable amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Riches? I haue read of ſome, as <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hauing ſent him from king <hi>Alexander</hi> thirty thouſand tallents of go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, he refuſed it, returning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſweare, that it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s for kinges to vſe mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y and not for Philoſophers, and <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> a mighty monarche had riches ſo much in contempt, that hee thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rich <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ough by gouerning ſuch as had th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, though be poſſeſſed none. This i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron age of ours affoordes not many ſo affected, but it is true that <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, <hi>maxime admira<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur cum qui pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mia non mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur:</hi> for mony is ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tall, as moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſure, and no man can w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t without miſery, <hi>abſque pecunia mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>è viuitur</hi> ſaith <hi>Terence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tantum quantum habes ſis,</hi> a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns credite is according to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14253:8"/> his wealth: doth not experience teach this, that the gentleman carrieth many a give that hath nothing but his birth to brag on, the ſcholler taketh many a skoffe, that hath nothing but his bookes to boaſt on, the ſouldier is little ſet by, that hath nothing but his buckler to ſhield him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid non pecunia poteſt,</hi> ſiluer aunſweareth to all, ſaith the Preacher. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.19. and true it is: for by it all other wants whatſoeuer are ſupplied. Is not the foole thought wiſe if hee hath wealth, and the wiſe fooliſh if he want it: who will reiect an Aſſe, if he come laden with gold, when few will accept a man if hee hath nothing but his wit. Doo not riches oftentimes preferre men to honour, for that cauſe <hi>Labans</hi> ſonnes enuied <hi>Iacob,</hi> becauſe hée had got honor by their fathers goods. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.1. Doo we not ſée that ſuch as haue béene much renowned when they had riches, haue loſt theyr dignity when they decayed, who was more repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of in proſperity then <hi>Iob,</hi> but when his goods were gone, hee could ſay. <hi>Iob.</hi> 19.9. that he was ſpoyled of his honour.</p>
               <p>Therefore Riches are of great price and praiſe, they were one of the giftes God gaue <hi>Salomon,</hi> yet he poſſeſsing as great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſiluer as ſtones, could ſay, <hi>A good Name is to be choſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue great Riches, Prou.</hi> 22.1. A Philoſopher yéeldeth a pretie reaſon, Riches may bee recouered when they are loſt, but a good Name can neuer: for as <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith, the infamy of a man is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall, ſhée liueth when you thincke her loſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good Name is better then pretious ointments.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat more ſoueraigne for many vſes in Phiſicke then ointments, dayly experience approoues it.</p>
               <p>In the time of the old law, ointmentes were ſo coſtly in compounding, ſo artificiall in compoſing, ſo precious in accompt, that they were called holy ointments. <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.23. becauſe they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſerue for certaine vſes of the Tabernacle.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid that <hi>Mary</hi> annointed the féete of Chriſt with a pound
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14253:8"/> of ointment of ſpikenard very coſtly, the ſauour whereof filled the whole houſe.</p>
               <p>Quéene <hi>Saba</hi> brought pretious odours and oyntmentes, for a preſent to king <hi>Salomon:</hi> for ointments are part of a kings trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> had men of purpoſe appointed to that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. 2. <hi>King,</hi> 20.13. and ſo had <hi>Hezekiah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Loue is an excellent thing, yet the loue of brethren is likened to the pretious ointment that ranne downe <hi>Aarons</hi> beard, as appée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the Pſalmes.</p>
               <p>The Church is greatly to be exalted, yet the Church reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth her good Name to ointments, as appéereth in the Canticles.</p>
               <p>Ointments in reſpect of their neceſſitie in vſe, efficacie, in ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and odoriferous ſauours, are to bee accompted very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and profitable, Yet ſaith the Preacher, <hi>A good Name is better then a good ointment. Eccleſ.</hi> 7.3. and it ſtandeth wyth reaſon: for oyntments may preſerue and pleaſure ſuch as liue, but they cannot benefite a man when his body is dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good Name is better then long life.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat more deſired amongſt men th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> length of dayes, <hi>vita incundiſsima,</hi> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all he hath to prolong his life, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> by the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed wom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, which ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt all thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Mark.</hi> 5.26.</p>
               <p>And certes although the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> aſhes, Ice congealed of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> conuert to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and man made of earth muſt diſſolue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>: for <hi>omni aetati mortem eſſe communem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And albeit the beſt Pipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> then the Crab, the ſwéeteſt flower, ſooner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the better man ſhall ſometime ſooner die th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rate, <hi>Abel</hi> was cut off when <hi>Cayn</hi> was permitted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> liue to his reproach.</p>
               <p>Yet commonly in the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riptures, the benefite of a long life is accompted a great bleſsing: (ſo a mans déedes be aunſwearable to his dayes, otherwiſe the more old, the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ible <hi>Prou.</hi> 16.31.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14253:9"/> there is nothing more reprochfull ſaith <hi>Seneca,</hi> then an old man, which hath none other argument to prooue he hath liued long, but onely his yeares:) for it is ſaide of the godly, hee ſhall goe to his graue in a full age, as a ricke of corne commeth in due ſeaſon into the barne, <hi>Iob.</hi> 5.26.</p>
               <p>The Lord promiſed the people of Ieruſalem this bleſſing, there ſhall yet olde men and olde wemen dwell therein, and euery man with his ſtaffe in his hand for very age <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.4.</p>
               <p>It is ſaid of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Abraham,</hi> he died in a good age, an old man, and of great yeares, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25.8.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iſaack,</hi> hee died, and was gathered vnto his people being old and full of dayes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.29.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauid,</hi> hee died in a good age, and full of dayes, 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.28.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iob,</hi> he died being old and full of dayes, <hi>Iob.</hi> 42.17</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Now it is ſaid concerning the wicked, that he ſhall not liue out halfe his dayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55, 23. but ſhall bée cut off before his tyme, <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.32. We haue example in <hi>Saul,</hi> when hee killed himſelfe, and in <hi>Iudas</hi> when he hanged himſelfe: the Lord layeth this as a iudgement vpon <hi>Ely,</hi> there ſhall not bee an old man in his houſe, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.31.</p>
               <p>Yet a good Name is better then a long life, the Wiſeman ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth a reaſon. <hi>A good life hath the dayes nombred, but a good Name endureth for euer. Eccleſ.</hi> 41.13. the common ſtate of life, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, is 70. or 80. yeares, but ſay (that none liuing euer ſaw) any ſhould attaine the age of <hi>Methuſhelah</hi> 979. yéers, yet his dayes are definite and determinable, but his Name re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes memorable to all poſterities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14253:9"/>
               <head>A good Name better then a Frend.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat man can want the ſocietie and ſolace of a true frend: the Whale muſt haue his fiſh to direct him, and man his frend to delight him.</p>
               <p>Without a frend to participate withall, there is nothing ſo delightfull to the eye, ſo delectable to the eare, ſo ioyfull to the hart, that could procure vs any pleaſure.</p>
               <p>What more neceſſary then a frend, in wealth to accompany, in wo to comfort, in any eſtate to communicate with.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> was often in daunger of his life but for <hi>Ionathan: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſimus</hi> was a great frend to <hi>Paul</hi> in his diſtreſſe: the wounded man had béene dead but for the <hi>Samaritane.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is comparable to a true frend, if we ſearch into all ſectes and ſortes of people.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Amongſt the common ſort.</head>
                  <p>THeir loue is more light then loyall, in croſſes like the Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold, which cloſe with euery cloud: in wealth like y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Drone, which draweth from the Bée: in both like the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lipe, which chaunge with euery obiect, ſuch as gaue <hi>Chriſt</hi> good entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at his comming to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> could cry <hi>Crucif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> to haue him to the croſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Amongſt neighbours.</head>
                  <p>THeir frendſhip is more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> then faithfull: if they bée rich, they can hardly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ell together. <hi>Lot</hi> could not away with <hi>Abraham,</hi> becauſe their riches were ſo great. If rich and poore dwell together, then the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> to the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll. <hi>Diues</hi> could not abide <hi>Lazarus</hi> becauſe he was poore. If artificers and tradesmen dwell together, then they be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, according to the common ſaying, <hi>Figulus figulum odit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:14253:10"/>
                  <head>Amongſt kinſfolkes.</head>
                  <p>THere goodwill is as commonly cold as kinde, like the Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wort, which fléeth from the vine, though it bee planted neuer ſo néere: for the common prouerbe is verified, Many kinſfolkes few frendes: <hi>Saul</hi> could not abide <hi>Dauid</hi> for all he married his daughter, nor <hi>Laban</hi> loued not <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Amongſt Brothers.</head>
                  <p>ALas it is lamentable, that thoſe which bée nigheſt in bloud ſhould bée furtheſt from beneuolence: ſome carry malice till oportunity may effect it, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did toward <hi>Iacob,</hi> becauſe his father was liuing. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.41. Some conſpire death as <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren did againſt him, becauſe his father loued him beſt: ſome commit murder, as <hi>Cayn</hi> did to <hi>Abel,</hi> becauſe his ſacrifice was better accepted of God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. ſuch is the loue of brethren, that it may well be true that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>A frend is neerer then a brother. Prou.</hi> 18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Amongſt parents and children.</head>
                  <p>IT is horrible to expreſſe the vnnaturall practiſes of ſuch, whome nature hath appropriated ſo néere: was not <hi>Senacherib</hi> ſlayne by his owne children: and did not <hi>Nero</hi> murther <hi>Agrippina</hi> his owne mother.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Betwene man and wife.</head>
                  <p>THis of all other is the néereſt coniunction, and yet a man is croſt with a collop of his owne fleſh. What a torment was <hi>Iobs</hi> wife to him in his trouble, was not <hi>Ahab</hi> brought to confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by <hi>Iezebels</hi> counſell, did not <hi>Delilah</hi> ſéeke <hi>Sampſons</hi> deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction when he ſatiſfied her deſire.</p>
                  <p>I know there be many (els God forbid) that perfourme all the dueties of loue and nature within the former deſcribed kindes, but they are vſed and executed, not by thoſe which are enemies but Frendes: for a frend ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> loueth at all times. <hi>Prou.</hi> 17.17. and without loue there is none ſo néere ingraffed by nature but liue diſſeuered and at diſcord by enmity, therefore a frend is moſt to be preferred.</p>
                  <p>What is hée will doe ſo much as one frend for an other. Some brothers are very naturall. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did kindly nouriſh his brothers
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14253:10"/> in their age, which would cruelly haue killed him in his youth. <hi>Gen.</hi> 50.21. and <hi>Iudah</hi> did offer to ſtay in a ſtrange countrey as a pledge for his brother <hi>Beniamin,</hi> and was in great daunger of diſpleaſure. <hi>Gen.</hi> 44.23. Yet one frend hath done more for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then this. I haue read of <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithias,</hi> how the one béeing condemned to die, and crauing ſome liberty to ſée his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie before his death, the other ſtaid behind as a ſuertie for his ſafe returne, and to receiue his puniſhment if the other broke promiſe.</p>
                  <p>Some children are very duetifull, yet they will ſometime doo as much for their frend as their father. <hi>Ionathan</hi> loued <hi>Saul</hi> well, yet he loued his frend <hi>Dauid</hi> as his owne ſoule, though his father could not abide him. A frend wil ſometime do more for a man then his owne child. Was not <hi>Huſhai Dauids</hi> frend true to him when <hi>Abſalon</hi> his ſonne was a traytor to him.</p>
                  <p>A man loues his child well: yet hée had rather ſometyme haue his children iniuried then his frendes. <hi>Lot</hi> had rather haue his daughters defloured then his frendes abuſed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.8.</p>
                  <p>Some wemen loue their huſbandes ſo intierly, that they had rather die then depart with them. <hi>Admetus</hi> hauing a diſeaſe running vpon him which could not be cured without the death of an other, could find none that would gladly dye for his ſake but his wife <hi>Alceſti Arthemiſia</hi> did drincke the aſhes of hir huſband after his death, becauſe ſhée would haue her owne body <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> bee her huſbands graue. In the country called <hi>Getica,</hi> the we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n deſire to die on their huſbandes bodies and to bée buried with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, and becauſe their cuſtome is to marry many wemen, there is great ſtriuing which ſhal haue the preferment and pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe herein. Yet one frend hath done for another as much as this. I haue read of <hi>Ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes</hi> and <hi>Pylades,</hi> how <hi>Oreſtes</hi> was con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed to dye, and the Iudge not knowing one from another, <hi>Pylades</hi> ſayd his name was <hi>Oreſtes</hi> to ſaue his fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s life. <hi>Tanta eſt vis amicitiae,</hi> that as <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, a true frend is <hi>tanquam alter idem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quod difficile dulce,</hi> as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> rare to find, ſo it is a great treaſure to attaine one, as no doubt a true frend is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of earthly ioy. Yet a good Name is f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r better then the beſt frend: for the beſt frendes of all will forſake vs when we dye, but a good
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14253:11"/> Name will remaine after death: <hi>Poſt fatum fama triumphat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sithence a good Name is more excellent then any thing: Wée muſt not looke to get it by ſiniſter, but by ſingular meanes, not by vile, but by vertuous actions, not by vayne, but by valiant at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptes. The Philoſopher ſaith well. <hi>Nec vero clarorum viro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum poſt mortem honores permanerent, ſi nihil eorum ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum animi efficerent, quò diutius memoriam ſui teneremus:</hi> for it is the commendable actions of a man in his life that makes his Name renowned and memorable after death. As for example, if a good man die what will the people report of him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If he be a godly Maieſtrate.</head>
                  <p>THey will thus commend him. He was in the common wealth like <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> prouident in foreſéeing, in geuing iudgement like <hi>Samuel:</hi> iuſt without bribes, in caſes of counſell like <hi>Salomon,</hi> prudent in aduiſing, amongſt his inferiours like <hi>Saul,</hi> little in hys owne ſight: Hée ſtood not vpon the countenance, but accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his office: he was full of piety, much pitifull, nothing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall, he was obeyed more for loue then feare, his bleſſed death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed his godly life, and our bad deſertes were meanes to abridge his dayes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If he be a good Miniſter.</head>
                  <p>THey will report of him, He was a good Phiſition? for hée not onely fed our ſoules with many good ſermons, but hee refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed our bodies with many good meales, hee was beloued and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured of all, not ſo much for his title, as integrity. He was right <hi>Pauls</hi> ſucceſſor: for hee was plaine in his habite without pride, painefull in his calling without repyning. A paſtor for deuiding the woord, A patterne for direction of life, He might boldly reproue vs for our ſinnes, becauſe he liued blameleſſe in our ſightes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If he be a vertuous rich man.</head>
                  <p>THey will thus deſcribe him, He was not onely rich by reaſon of his wealth, but well doing: his houſe was an Inne for the ſtraunger, an hoſpitall for the poore, a repaſt for his neighbours: his purſe was proſtrate for euery good purpoſe: hee imitated <hi>Iob</hi> for integrity, <hi>Abraham</hi> for hoſpitality, <hi>Moſes</hi> for humility: hée was louing to his equals, lowly to his inferiors, liberall to all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14253:11"/> men: We might well forbeere many miſers that be about vs, but we haue a great miſſe of ſuch a man to liue amongſt vs.</p>
                  <p>If he be any other of what practiſe, profeſſion, faculty or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſo euer, he muſt expect like commendation according to his conuerſation, obſeruing the dignities, degrées, giftes, and graces of euery one: for as the Cedar trée is further ſéene then the ſhrub, ſo the higher a man be in place, the greater is his report: the more noble the more notorious is the Name, like a lampe which is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſéene vpon a tower, then in a trenche.</p>
                  <p>I will (for breuity) omit millions of woorthy men whoſe Names are famoſed by their apparant workes and writings, and becauſe (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) the actes and not the ſame ſhould firſt be conſidered, I referre you to their actions, to iudge the worthineſſe of the Authors.</p>
                  <p>If I ſhould enter into authenticall examples, how many haue left renowned Names to the world, as it is recorded in the word, it were too prolixious, and néedeleſſe, becauſe they be very perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, yet I will infer a few as an introduction to the reſt.</p>
                  <p>It is written of
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> that hée was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> through all the world. <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 6.27.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Samuel,</hi> that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.26.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Dauid,</hi> that his Name was m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> vnto the Name of the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.9.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Salomon,</hi> that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap> 1. <hi>King</hi> 10.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iob,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> like hym i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> the earth. <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.3.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>If I ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> worthy Names in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them. Yet amon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> many (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> then any, reſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of the ſexe) what a rare report hath our Souer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap> Lady <hi>Queene Elizabeth</hi> deſerued? Whoſe patience in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:14253:12"/> croſſes, whoſe piety in mainetayning the Goſpell, whoſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in foreſéeing for her Countries, whoſe pitty diſperſed to all her ſubiectes, hath made her Name ſo renowned, that it is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly carryed into the South for <hi>Saba</hi> to woonder at, but into moſt partes of the world, for all to admire at.</p>
                  <p>Her fame maketh forrayners to ſtand in feare of her: her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty maketh the Pagans to be amazed at her: her Regiment ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all nations to maruaile at her. Bleſſed is ſhe that hath ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſinges: happy are we that haue ſo rare a Phenix: Accurſed be they that wiſh ill to ſuch a creature. As ſhée hath deſerued an admirable Name by her life: <hi>Sic tandiu laudabitur dum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria rerum Anglorum manebit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If a good Name gotten by laudable meanes doth magnifie a man: an ill Name procéeding of miſdemeanor, muſt néedes infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mize him. For as the ſame tallow which doth cherriſh the light, doth extinguiſh it, if it be turned downeward: ſo the ſame mouth which dooth praiſe one, dooth depraue him if his actions bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious: as for example, if an ill man die, what will they ſay of him?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If he be an vngodly Gouernour.</head>
                  <p>They will thus report: The Towne hath a happy turne by his death: for it had no d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>te by his life: he did conuert the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like commodity priuately into his owne coffers: he was ready to hang a man like <hi>Haman,</hi> for bowing of a knée or moouing a cap: he ſtood ſo much vpon his Magiſtracy, that hee cleane forgot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be a man. In his Office he would many wayes be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſometime for feare of offending others, as <hi>Pilate</hi> was, who condempned Chriſt for fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>pleaſe <hi>Ceſar:</hi> ſometime with loue he bare to his fréendes, like <hi>Herod,</hi> who to pleaſe the loue of a damſell, condemned <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to death: ſometime with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, like the chiefe Prieſtes, who of malice condemned <hi>Paul</hi> to be ſmitten as ſtoned without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>: ſometime with gold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, like the children of the Prophet <hi>Samuel:</hi> ſometime with letters, as the Elders and Nobles of <hi>Izreel</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re by the meanes of <hi>Iezabel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14253:12"/>
                  <head>If he be a lewd Miniſter.</head>
                  <p>What will they ſay: The Church hath béene rather troubled then taught by him, he was called by the Name of the <hi>Rephaims,</hi> but he might well be counted in the nomber of the <hi>Zamzummins:</hi> he was a dumb dog that could not barke, a blinde watchman that could not ſée, a wandring good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that could not direct: he played the Fox vnder the ſhadow of a Phariſee: he was no paſtor but a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, no <hi>Paul</hi> but a <hi>Saul,</hi> no pillar of the Church for his vertue, but a piller for his aduauntage: Happy is he if he died well: for wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched are they that haue a worſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>If he be a wicked wealthy man.</head>
                  <p>They will ſet him foorth after this ſort: The Country is well rid of a catterpiller: for hée was a great incroacher of commons, a gréeuous inhancer of Rentes, ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e of oppreſſion to all men: his buildinges were more ſumptuous then his beneuolence: for he cherriſhed the poore with his meate, as the catt doeth the miſe: he was in ability like the rich man that inlarged his houſes, in libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity like <hi>Nabal</hi> in refreſhing <hi>Dauids</hi> ſouldiours, in charity like <hi>Diues</hi> in relieuing <hi>Lazarus,</hi> in his diet like <hi>Diogines</hi> for his groſſe féeding, he euer had aboundance, yet liued like a beggar: but now he is become a banckerout: for the world ſtriueth for his mucke, the wormes for his fleſh, whereſoeuer his ſoule be.</p>
                  <p>If he be any other, of what calling or condition ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, hée ſhalbe ſure to haue like ſame according to his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes, ſuch proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſuch report, euery man at his death ſhalbe ſpoken of after his deſartes. Some will ſpeake of experience: many, of ſpight: moſt, of report: all, as they be affected or informed. Beſides, we are to conſider the callings and countenaunce of men: for as the higher obiect is furtheſt in ſight: ſo the more high, the more haynous, the more mighty the more miſerable is the fall, and as the whiter lawne hath the déeper mole, ſo the more holy man, the more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible is his offence.</p>
                  <p>I will diſcend into a few examples of the ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ny of an euill Name, that their terrible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> might de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erre o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> the like.</p>
                  <p>For cruelty, what a Name hath <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14253:13"/> them? if but in this one, in willing all the male <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to be ſlaine by the Midwiues at their birthes: the other in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding al the male children to be ſlaine in <hi>Bethelem</hi> from two yeares old and vnder.</p>
                  <p>For treachery, what a Name hath <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; one for working treaſon againſt his owne father; the other for betraying his owne maiſter?</p>
                  <p>For vnnaturall dealing, what a Name hath <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Sane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheribs</hi> children left in record, one in killing his owne brother, the other in murdering their owne father.</p>
                  <p>He that ſaith, <hi>The memoriall of the iuſt is bleſſed,</hi> dooth adde this: <hi>The Name of the wicked ſhall rot. Prou.</hi> 10.6. as we haue experience by theſe which are expreſſed: for as rotten fruite doth caſt a ſtinking ſauour when it is applied to the noſthrils: ſo a lewd man doth make his Name very lothſome, when his oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious actions are called to memory.</p>
                  <p>We commonly ſay, that he which hath loſt his Name is halfe hanged: and certes, to haue no Name or an ill Name, is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted a great croſſe: the Lord impoſeth this as a puniſhment vpon the wicked, <hi>His Name ſhalbe put out from vnder heauen. Deut.</hi> 9.14. and 28.20. as hee did by <hi>Amalek: and ſhalbe no more remembred. Iob.</hi> 24.20.</p>
                  <p>Some carry a Name throughout the word, an other through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Realme, ſome within a Countie, many within a towne, moſt within a ſtréete: but to haue no Name, not ſo much as in a ſtréete, as it is the leaſt report, ſo it is the greater reproche: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iob</hi> ſpeaking of the wicked, ſayth, <hi>His remembraunce ſhall periſh from the earth, and he ſhall haue no Name in the ſtreet. Iob.</hi> 18.17.</p>
                  <p>An ill Name is ſo odious, that <hi>Moſes</hi> made a law for the ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, that he ſhould pay one hundred ſickels for bringing vp an ill Name of a mayde. <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.19.</p>
                  <p>An ill Name (whoſe conſiſtence is in contemptible actions) doth cauſe reproach and ſhame, which bee ſo burdenous to fleſh and bloud, that <hi>Dauid</hi> in diuers places of his Pſalmes, doth not onely deſire to haue rebuke and ſhame taken from him, but alſo be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14253:13"/> for no worſer plague to light vppon his ennemies. <hi>Fill their faces with ſhame. Pſal.</hi> 83. <hi>Socrates</hi> could ſay, it was better to die honeſtly then to liue ſhamefully, it is ſuch an abhorrency in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and no meruaile: for it is an argument of Gods indignation: after the Lord (by the mouth of the Prophet) had reuealed all the Iudgements he would afflict Ieruſalem with, hee doth aggrauate the puniſhment by this <hi>Epiphonema. So thou ſhalt bee as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and ſhame. Ezek.</hi> 5.15.</p>
                  <p>An ill Name doth not onely diſparage and impeach the Agent, but ſuch as be allied to him; not onely the party, but his progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and ſuch as belong or be any way deriued from his linage.</p>
                  <p>The reprochfull déedes of the child doth ſomewhat impaire the Name of his parents: the Wiſeman ſaith, <hi>an euill nurtured ſon is the diſhonour of the father, Eccl.</hi> 22.3. Therefore it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> that <hi>if a prieſtes daughter fall to play the whore, ſhe poluteth her father, Leuit.</hi> 21.9. The ill report of <hi>Eli</hi> his ſonnes was ſome diſgrace to himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>The infamous actes of the father muſt néedes be ſome blemiſh to the child, that fruite can hardly flouriſh on the trée which is rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten at the roote, that peſtiferous act of <hi>Cain</hi> was a diſcountenance to all that came of his loynes.</p>
                  <p>It is no paradoxe (the more is the pitty) to ſée the fault of the father caſt as an obloquy in the téeth of the child, and the parentes to be often twitted and vpbrayded for the eſcapes of their children.</p>
                  <p>There is many a blaſted braunch that comes of an auncient houſe, that ſuppoſeth his ill Name may be famozed by the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned factes of his forefathers, and to couer his impiety by his peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée: but ſuch are vainely ſeduced. What auayles (ſayth <hi>S. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi>) noble linage to him which is with villanous manners reproched. <hi>Saluſt</hi> hath a ſenſible ſaying to that effect, The more honorable the life of the Aunceſtors is after eſtéemed, the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfull is the vice of the linage that ſuccéede them. It hath bene an old ſaying, that it is a good ſtocke where there is neither whore or thiefe ſpring out of it, and yet (ſuch is the efficacy of iniquity) that ſome flagitious crime is many times a ſtayne to a whole ſtocke, ſome that are co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>cted of egregious and capitall offences,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14253:14"/> are a taynting to the whole progeny, as rebels, traytors, and ſuch like. The ſonne of <hi>Syrach</hi> ſayth, that <hi>if children be proud with haughtineſſe and fooliſhnes, they defile the nobility of theyr kindred. Eccl.</hi> 22.9. It makes me call to minde that prety aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare of <hi>Iphicrates</hi> that valiant captaine, who béeing imbraided by his baſe birth, béeing but a Shoomakers ſonne) by <hi>Hermodius</hi> a noble man borne, yet of bad behauiour, gaue him this glike, my bloud taketh beginning in mée, and thine her farewell at thée: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thereby that a poore ſtocke is no reproch to him which is with good manners adorned, when gentry may bee diſparaged by ſome obſcene action in the generation.</p>
                  <p>It is not the Name, but the quallities, not dignity or diſcent, but the diſpoſition and good demeanor, that makes any renowned and famous.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Ierome</hi> ſayth, the chiefeſt nobility before God is to excell in all vertue. <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> ſayth, he is honourable which diſdayneth to doo ſeruice to ſinne. <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth, he that will eſtéeme a man true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, muſt behold him naked laying aſide poſſeſſions, authority, and other fables of fortune, and ſée what hee hath beſide of himſelfe. One aduiſing <hi>Bias</hi> to conuay away all his goods and treaſure bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ennemies ſacked the Towne, <hi>Sic ago</hi> ſaith hée: <hi>nam om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia mea mecum porto:</hi> eſtéeming hys inwarde gyftes to be his goods, and all the reſt to be but <hi>ludibria fortunae,</hi> which are moſt fortunate to fooles, <hi>fortuna fauet fatuis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Neceſſary obiections.</head>
               <p>It may be obiected, that there was neuer <hi>Chriſolite</hi> ſo pure, but that it would ſtayne, or fruite ſo faire, but that would infect: or Iron ſo bright, but that it would ruſt; or man ſo rare, but may do amiſſe: <hi>For in many thinges we ſinne all.</hi> Inſomuch as none can be accompted ſo abſolutely good, but may leaue behind him as well an euill Name, which procéedeth of his infirmity, as a good Name which followeth his conformity, as for example.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Abraham</hi> was the <hi>Father</hi> of the faithfull, yet he was a <hi>Forger</hi> of lies.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Noah</hi> was the Preacher of righteouſnes, yet he was impeached with dronkenneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14253:14"/>
               <p>Though <hi>Dauid</hi> was famo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for his piety and exploites, yet he was defamed for his adultery and homicide.</p>
               <p>It may alſo be alleadged on the part of the reprobate, that there is no ſoyle ſo barren, but may yéeld ſome corne: no trie ſo bare, but may affoord ſome fruite: nor any man ſo bad, but may leaue ſome matter woorth the memoriall.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Pharaoh</hi> was a wicked rebellour, yet he prouided for the Prieſtes in the time of famine.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Saul</hi> was a notable Idolatour, yet hee put away the Sorcerers and Southſayers out of his land.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Iudas</hi> deceiued hys maiſter by treaſon, yet hee might winne many ſoules with his preaching.</p>
               <p>Theſe obiections are friuolous: for it is our vſuall manner of phraſe, to reuolue a mans fault in reuealing of his fame.</p>
               <p>If he be a godly man, he is ſet foorth with his defectes thus: hée was a graue man for gouernement, but very haſty: or thus, he was a learned man in the pulpit, but ſomewhat inſolent: or thus, he was very wiſe, but too too wanton. <hi>Dauid</hi> is prayſed with hys impedimentes in the 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15.5. It is written of him that he did that which was right in the ſight of the Lord, and turned from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that he commaunded him all the dayes of his life: hetherto he is commended, but it followes, Saue only in the matter of <hi>Vriah</hi> the Hittite, héere appeares his imperfection.</p>
               <p>If he bee a lewd-man, hee is commonly phraſed out thus, hee would once a yeare feaſt the poore, but all the yeare after oppreſſe them, or thus, he erected a braue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ding to the eye, but the ſtones in the wall may cry for violence: or thus, he was a proper man to ſight, but we may ſée his ouerſight: Experience offereth plenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull examples of ſuch perſons.</p>
               <p>So that now we are to conſider the difference betwéene the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and diſſolute man.</p>
               <p>The godly ſometime ſhall not differ from the wicked in fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>g but in riſing: for we ſée that <hi>Dauid</hi> committed murther as well as <hi>Cain:</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> idolatry, as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll as <hi>Saul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The godly ſhall ſometime adde ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to ſinne with the wicked, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did in homicide after adultery, and inſec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ity after h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14253:15"/> till <hi>Nathan</hi> reprooued hym. And as <hi>Peter</hi> did in forſwearing hys Maſter after many denyals: yet we muſt not ballance a bad man with the better: for one ſinne of weakeneſſe with repentance, the other of malice with perſeuerance.</p>
               <p>The wicked haue their liues as full of ſpots as the Leopard, ſo the beſt haue their blemiſhes: but what then? who will compare <hi>Noah</hi> with notorious dronkards: or <hi>Dauid</hi> with common adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers: or <hi>Peter</hi> with common periurers: or ſome poore ſinner with euery prophane offendour: or him that takes but one trip in his life, with thoſe which allwayes tread awry?</p>
               <p>Though the roſe be cancker-eaten, it is not to bee caſt away, though lawne haue a little ſtayne, it is not to bee déemed ſtarcke naught: no more muſt the beſt man, although he hath a fault, be ſtraight accompted infamous: for as the brightneſſe of the Sunne doth blemiſh the light of the Moone, ſo the fame of his good actions doth obſcure the folly of his eſcapes. The Apoſtle calleth <hi>Lot,</hi> iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> though he committed inceſt: and <hi>Noah,</hi> the eight Preacher of righteouſneſſe, though he ſinned in ebriety: becauſe moſt of their actions were good and commendable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A good obſeruation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſpice finem,</hi> it is wiſedome to be ſparing of ſpeech. and not to be too cenſoriall of any man, eyther in <hi>primordio,</hi> or <hi>medio,</hi> but to prayſe the ende, remembring this pithy period of <hi>Pliny, one day deemeth another, but the laſt geueth iudgment of all that is paſt.</hi> To obtrect him raſhly, whom we may haue cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, or to exalt another vaynely, where wee may haue cauſe to recant. <hi>infipientis, non ſapientis eſt,</hi> I take it to be a point of folly.</p>
               <p>Many a good man may haue a bad beginning, and yet haue an excellent end, ſo had <hi>Paul,</hi> at the firſt he was a gréeuous perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, afterward became a glorious Apoſtle, ſo was <hi>Manaſſes:</hi> at firſt he was a monſtrous Idolater, afterward béecame a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous conuert.</p>
               <p>Many a godly man may haue a good entrance at the firſt, but a great fall afterwarde, and yet prooue laudable at the laſt: ſo had <hi>Dauid,</hi> at the firſt, who more godly, afterward who more grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in that matter of <hi>Vriah?</hi> ſo had <hi>Peter,</hi> at the firſt, who more
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14253:15"/> ready to follow Chriſt? afterward hee forſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re him: yet in the ende theyr penitency excéeded their impiety.</p>
               <p>Many an euill man may haue a good beginning and yet c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me to a ſhamefull ende: ſo had <hi>Amaziah:</hi> for in the beginning of his raigne he carryed an externall ſhew of ſanctity, afterward he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an Idolater and adored the Idols of the Idumeans: ſo had <hi>Rehoboam:</hi> for during thrée yeares hee did well, afterward hee fell to all wickedneſſe: ſo had Iudas: for at the firſt he was choſen for an Apoſtle, in the end he was conuicted of treaſon.</p>
               <p>So that it is diſtance of time that doth diſtinguiſh the déedes of men, and the end of theyr dayes that geueth iuſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e of reports. <hi>Plato</hi> calleth him happy that may attayne in his laſt age ſo wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and good life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Comparatiue conſiderations.</head>
               <p>Is a good Name ſo excellent, that it is better then any riches, more pretious then coſtly oyntmentes, more eſtim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble then length of dayes, more durable then the beſt frendes? then let vs e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this comparatiue conſideration.</p>
               <p>What is he that will leaue any paynes vndertaken that may make to his enriching? <hi>Suauis eſt odor lucri,</hi> the ſcholler will imploy his arte, the ſouldior his armes, the marchant will croſſe the ſeas, the Lawyer will toſſe his books, the tradeſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>peth his trauell, and moſt men their time to get earthly treaſure.</p>
               <p>What is he that would not ſéeke all the beſt oyntmentes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they neuer ſo pretious, all the beſt ſalues bee they neuer ſo ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, both of them, be they neuer ſo déere, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, if hée were in daunger?</p>
               <p>What is he that were at the point of death, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not geue all his mucke, vſe all the meanes, ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r any miſery to prolong his life? we read of <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ahazariah,</hi> how in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſought onely to Phiſitions, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the other to witches, and forſooke God, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th to dye.</p>
               <p>What is he that hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ther h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>manity or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not doo much for an vnfayned fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>? a man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet he wil not let to giue th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to do his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> pretious, yet he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it for hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frendes ſake, as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14253:16"/> appéeres in <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Pithias.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then if riches, oyntmentes, life, and frendes are ſo pretious, who would not practiſe all the wayes, apply all the beſt meanes, and aduenture all he hath to purchaſe that which is farre better then any of them, <hi>A good Name?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How to get a good Name.</head>
               <p>It is an eaſie matter to get a Name, to bee ſpoken of. Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, rebels, and moſt malefactors are not without a Name, as <hi>Abſalom</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> for treaſon: <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> for rebellion: <hi>Achitophel, Simon Magus,</hi> and many other for theyr peſtiferous Actions. We haue had lamentable experience of the diſloyall practiſes of too many within this lande, whoſe Names are not yet forgotten, though the Crowes haue deuoured theyr carkaſſes. But as their déedes were deteſtable, ſo their memoriall doth not turne to theyr prayſe but reproach.</p>
               <p>There be many that thincke it a credite to kill a man, a matter of commendation to carrouſe well, a braue grace to blaſpheme, a great glory to boaſt of theyr beaſtlineſſe: but as they take all their pride in impiety, ſo they ſhall be ſpoken of, but how? not to theyr glory, but diſgrace: not to theyr credite, but ſhame, as the Lord threatned the people in <hi>Hoſeas</hi> time, that (for their iniquity) <hi>hee would chaunge their glory into ſhame. Hoſea.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>But to get a good Name as it is hard, ſo it is honourable: as it is rare, ſo it is renowned: as it is moſt pretious, ſo it is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of prayſe.</p>
               <p>Thinges of great price are not got without much payne: the ſcholler muſt turne many leaues ere he become learned, the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier muſt ſuffer many conflictes ere he returne conqueror, and hée that will haue a good Name muſt vſe all induſtrious meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne it, <hi>vt tales nos eſſe putamus, vt iure laudemur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is no man (ſayth the Heathen man) in whome there is not this deſire, rather to be prayſed then ill ſpoken of. Then let vs practiſe ſuch thinges as deſerue prayſe: for as <hi>Tully</hi> ſayth, <hi>vera gloria radices agit atque etiam propagatur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The worſt wretch that is, dooth wiſh to bee well thought on, though he neglect the meanes to manifeſt it. Then if wée will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14253:16"/> glory and a good Name, let vs follow that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>table ſaying of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who teacheth this to be a direct and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> courſe: <hi>Si quis ageret, vt qualis haberi vellet, talis eſſet,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ry one ſhould labour to be indéede, that which he loues to be accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that is commendable.</p>
               <p>He that will haue a good Name, muſt ſtretch his talent on the tayneters, and make his giftes gliſter like gold in the eyes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: for the greateſt prayſe conſiſteth not in poſſeſſing, but diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them.</p>
               <p>If thou haſt béene trayned vp in good litterature, let thy profite appéere to others: for as <hi>Plato</hi> ſayth, we are not onely borne for our ſelues, but partly our country, partly our frends clayme an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in our natiuity: and we haue examples of many who haue conſumed the whole courſe of their liues in the diſtribution of their learning. <hi>Diomedes</hi> wrote ſix thouſand bookes concerning Gram<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, as <hi>Plutarch</hi> reportes. <hi>Origen</hi> wrote ſeauen thouſand bookes of many matters. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> wrote ſo many bookes, that no man is able eyther to read them or come by them, as <hi>Tritenhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi> beléeueth: many heathen men haue bene ſo affected that way that ſome thought all theyr time loſt that was not ſpent in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as <hi>Scipio</hi> did, others would rather ſtarue then leaue their ſtudy, as <hi>Chryſippus</hi> did.</p>
               <p>If thou haſt wealth in aboundant meaſure, let thy ſaciety ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply an others miſery. Lend mony and corne to thy diſtreſſed neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> did when the people were oppreſſed: giue halfe thy goods to the poore as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did, entertayne ſtraungers as <hi>Lot</hi> did, Liue vprightly as <hi>Iob</hi> did.</p>
               <p>Geue to the mainetenance of ſchooles of learning, be a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to the forward Miniſters of the worde, erect Hoſpitals and Almeſhouſes for the reliefe of the impotent, Reſiſt not auctority, perſiſt in the trueth.</p>
               <p>It were too long to dilate all the meanes that may pertayne to the purchaſe of a good Name, conſidering it is got by euery lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble act, by perfection in any good profeſſion, whether he be learned or lay man, martiall or mechanicall, artiſt or artificer, hauing this diſtinction. 1. that the more exce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nt the practiſe is, the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14253:17"/> is the report: <hi>multo maiora ſunt opera animi quàm cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris</hi> ſaith <hi>Cicero,</hi> the giftes of the minde are farre more excellent then the actions of the body: <hi>caedant arma togae:</hi> although the valorous ſouldier is highly to be aduaunced: yet the Poet ſayth, he muſt geue place to learning, and good reaſon: for without expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience and learning the beſt Souldier ſhall haue bad ſucceſſe. For this cauſe, <hi>Alexander</hi> that valiant warriour would neuer goe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field without <hi>Caliſthenes</hi> a learned Philoſopher. 2. That as there be many exquiſite practitioners in this age, ſo he that doth more excell, is moſt to be exalted aboue others. Euery dunſiuall muſt not haue equiualent commendation with a Doctor, though both haue learning. Euery coward muſt not haue equall prayſe with a Captaine, though both can fight, nor euery bungler muſt not haue the like report as a good woorkeman, though both can worke: but he that is moſt rare in perfection, ſhould bee more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned in Name. <hi>Dauid</hi> had many valiant men of warre, and did deuide them into nombers according to their déedes and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, yet ſome were more honourable then other: for it is ſayd of <hi>Benaiah</hi> that hee had the Name amonge the thrée woorthies. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.22. 3. That the more ſingularitie any hath in ſundry giftes, the more illuſtrate is his glory. <hi>Dauid</hi> deſerues to be digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for many thinges: being a king for regiment: being a prophet for predication: béeing a warriour for proweſſe: béeing a man of ſmall ſtature, for his miraculous killing of the monſtrous Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine. There are many amongſt vs that are worthy to be memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized for many thinges (ſéeing naturall and litterall giftes were neuer more reſplendent in any age) but becauſe it were méeter for <hi>Mercurius</hi> to imblazon their actions then <hi>Battillus,</hi> I will omit them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What a good Name and Fame is:</head>
               <p>There are ſome that thinke many thinges to be famous, which in the owne nature are but ignoble and nothing woorth. The Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians do take it for a prayſe to eat their parents when they be dead, rather then wormes ſhould: the Iewes to marry in theyr owne Tribe, the Tryualles to kill their father when he is three ſcore yeares old and bren him, the wemen of <hi>Getica</hi> to be interred with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14253:17"/> their husbandes.</p>
               <p>There are ſome that ſuppoſe a good Name dependes onely vpon outward dignities, titles and termes of honor and renowne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vertuous actions: the Philoſopher dooth refute this: honour commeth not to vertue by dignities, but it commeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by vertue of them that vſe the dignitie. The very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of honor doth confirme it. <hi>Honor</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ariſtotle) is a reuerence geuen to an other for a teſtimony of his vertue.</hi> Therefore <hi>Catullus</hi> a vertuous man in Rome, ſéeing <hi>Nonius</hi> a very viti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> man ſytting in great dignity in his iuditiall ſeate, called him a ſwelling full of corruption, becauſe he knew his inward habite of the minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oppugnant to his outward honor he had amongſt men.</p>
               <p>There are ſome that thinke to purchaſe a ſame by ſetting forth fayre buildinges. <hi>Ornanda eſt dignitas domo, non ex domo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitas tota quaerenda eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tully:</hi> for, It is not the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhew of the houſe, but the godly actions of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that makes him renowned. If he be an ill man, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h <hi>Salomon? The houſe of the wicked ſhalbe deſtroyed: Prou.</hi> 14.11. then what ſhall become of all his glory?</p>
               <p>There are ſome that thinke they are famous onely for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity ſake, becauſe they iſſue from nobles or gentils. High <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euer béene eſtéemed. 1. <hi>Samu.</hi> 18.18. but yet if any degenerate from his progenitors, his birth cannot beautifie his baſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: it is not the grafting of a Crab vppon a Pippin ſtocke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> make it prooue a good apple, this is more fully refelled in the former part of this booke.</p>
               <p>There are ſome that thincke they are famous onely to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>compted wealthy: the Rich man was of this mind, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.19. <hi>They boaſt themſelues</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) in the multitude of their Riches. Pſal.</hi> 49.6. They gather goods and hope to leaue them to theyr children to mainetaine their Name: but what ſaith <hi>Iob</hi> to wicked worldlinges: <hi>he ſhall neither haue Sonne nor Neph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> amongſt his people, nor any poſterity in his dwellings. Iob<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8 19. ſo that ſhalbe verified which the Pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h, <hi>He ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ue his Riches for others. Pſal.</hi> 49. <hi>&amp;c. and ſhall h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e no Name at all. Iob.</hi> 18.17.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:14253:18"/>
               <p>A Poet ſaith, that Fame is nothing but a great ſwelling and filling of mens eares. This may be true, for (as <hi>Boetius</hi> ſayth) many haue often had great fame by the falſe opinion of the people, as <hi>Herode</hi> had when the people gaue a ſhout, ſaying, the voyce of God and not of man. <hi>Act.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>I take this to be a more perfect definition. Fame is a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of mens actions and déedes, aſwell farre off as nigh.</p>
               <p>The word Fame, as it is ſimply a ſubſtantiue, is aſwell indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and incident to bad men for their miſdemeanor, as to good men for their merites: but if Fame be taken in the better part, the adiunct good muſt bée connexed withall, and ſo it is called a good Fame: yet this adiunct is not alwayes vſuall, but the Fame is ſometime ſetfoorth by the effectes, as in this place, <hi>Queene Saba</hi> hearing the Fame (good is left out) of <hi>Salomon</hi> (but it followes by the effect) concerning the name of the Lord. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 10.1. came to prooue him with hard queſtions.</p>
               <p>Fame is a certaine kinde of knowledge, but not alwayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly of experience, but commonly vppon reporte, as may bée ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the 1. <hi>King.</hi> 10. therefore if we heare one prayſed and well reported, wée muſt not altogether beléeue our eares but our eyes, as <hi>Saba</hi> did, who trauayled of purpoſe to trie the truth of the report ſhe heard of <hi>Salomon:</hi> for <hi>a foole beleeueth all thinges. Pro.</hi> 14.15. and it ſtandeth with reaſon. Firſt, becauſe there may be more or leſſe reported then is true. <hi>Lo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Saba) the one halfe was not told me: for thou haſt more proſperity &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then I heard by report, or as it is in the</hi> 2. <hi>Chro.</hi> 9.6. <hi>thou exceedeſt the fame that I heard.</hi> Secondly, to confirme our Iudgements: for as <hi>Boetius</hi> ſaith, I doe not thinke the fauour or prayſe of the people woorthy to be remembred, that commeth not by wiſe and iuſt Iudgement.</p>
               <p>What ſhould be meant by a good Name I can hardly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, vnleſſe it be by a <hi>Metonymy,</hi> the Name put for the man or the actions of man: as the Name of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets are put for theyr writinges in <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.29. for we cannot properly ſay that a Name is ill, béecauſe in the beginning the firſt Name <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> was giuen by God: therefore a good Name importeth as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14253:18"/> much as prayſe and reporte, which ariſe by reaſon of the valiant and vertuous actions of men.</p>
               <p>It is recorded of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Mordecai,</hi> that his reporte went through all the kinges prouinces. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 9.4.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that he had good report of all men 3. <hi>Epiſt. Ioh. verſ.</hi> 12.</item>
                     <item>Many of our forefathers, that they ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>yn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d a good report. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.39.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe good Reports were grounded, and did grow of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent and laudable déedes of the Actors: and becauſe reportes are ſuch as doe commonly touch the Names and credites of men, the ſcripture willeth vs to practiſe ſuch thinges as bée of good reporte. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the <hi>Philippians</hi> to thincke of thoſe thinges that be of good report <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. and the ſame Apoſtle himſelfe was appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by good report and ill report. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.8. So that here is to be conſidered theſe thrée thinges. Firſt, that a wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>man muſt not meaſure his good Name and Fame altogether by the rumor of the people, but by the trueth of his conſcience, leaſt if he appéere other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then he is in déede, he be eaſely depriued of his glory by his ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and déedes. Who but the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> were exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for a time? but when their déedes came to be tried by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, then they prooued painted ſepulchers, to theyr ſhame. One falling into a Tyrantes hand, tooke vpon him the Name of a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher (more for vaineglory then vertue) the tyrant tolde hym if he were a Philoſopher, hée would patiently ſuffer iniuries and ill ſpéeches, and therefore would try him: and in déede did vrge hym to the vttermoſt, and ſo farre, as the Philoſopher was vexed, and ſaid he was not well dealt withall, becauſe he was a Philoſopher, the Tyrant gaue him this aunſweare: I had taken thee for a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, if thou hadſt held thy peace. Noting hereby, what a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ine thinge it is to appeare to be otherwiſe then we prooue to be. I hate ſuch men (ſaith <hi>Pacuuius</hi>) which in their actes be f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wordes Philoſophers. Secondly, that no man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſult of his owne actions, as the Scribes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> did. <hi>Laus proprio ſordeſcit in ore,</hi> ſaith the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Let an other man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14253:19"/> praiſe thee and not thy owne mouth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon. Pro.</hi> 27.2. For be the act neuer ſo excellent, a mans owne praiſe doth but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire it. <hi>Laudet fucatas qui vult extrudere merces,</hi> men vſe to praiſe their reffuſe ware, when they put it away. If it be good, the thing néedes no praiſe: the perfect Chorall néedes no colouring. Thirdly, that he which is ſo famous and renowned, muſt not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get himſelfe, but obſerue one wiſe pointe of <hi>Plato,</hi> that hée bée not proud when he is prayſed: and an other point of <hi>Tully,</hi> that he ſet not too light by that which men déeme of him: for that is a point of folly. The Philoſopher which was led but by the light of nature could ſay thus: if thou béeſt faire, thanke nature: if thou béeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of bloud, thancke thy parentes: if thou béeſt riche thancke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: if vertuous, praiſe God: and certes if we haue an eye to him that geueth all good giftes, we ſhall haue no cauſe to glory, if wée thincke vpon God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How daungerous it is to kepe a good Name.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Vch thinges as bée pretious cannot bée kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great perill. <hi>Abraham</hi> feared <hi>Sara,</hi> becauſe ſhe was faire, <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 12.11. For true it is that <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> ſaith, that which many deſire, one can hardly kepe ſafe, beauty is a great bliſſing, but a good Name is farre better: for one flouriſheth, when the other fadeth, therefore there is the more circumſpection requir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: the Poet ſaith, <hi>non minor eſt virtus quàm quaerere, parta tueri.</hi> the Philoſopher ſaith, to get wealth is the gifte of fortune: but to kepe it, is a point of wiſedome: then what is it to kéepe a good Name, which is farre better then wealth? Common experience doth teach vs this, that a good Name is like a merchants wealth, gotten in many yeares, but loſt in a moment.</p>
               <p>The faireſt bloſſome is ſooneſt blaſted with the winde, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt ſpring ſooneſt bitten with the froſt, and the beſt Name is ſooneſt blemiſhed by the maligna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. He that is famous and in better fauour aboue others, ſhalbe ſure to haue many meanes wrought to deface him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Starre <hi>Heſperus</hi> doth follow the Sunne,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14253:19"/> and the flies the hony: ſo dooth en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and ill tongues ſuch as be in honor and reputation. I néede not goe farre for examples, becauſe we ſée it dayly with our eyes: yet becauſe it ſhall appeare to be no new practiſe, I will repeat ſome examples out of the Scriptures. <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat</hi> much enuying the credite of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> that godly man, they hired one of purpoſe to prouo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for no other cauſe, but that they might haue an ill reporte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, to reproach him. <hi>Nehe.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Daniel</hi> was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> fauour with king <hi>Darius,</hi> and was in great eſtimation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: which the Rulers and Gouernours perceyuing, it ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpited them, that (although they could finde no iuſt occa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.4.) they ſought all poſſible meanes to diſgra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yea and to deſtroy him.</p>
               <p>So many wayes as malice may worke, ſo many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may be vſed to reproach and impeach a good Name.</p>
               <p>Haue we not had experience of ſome vicious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that haue yéelded their veſſels to villany to one, and haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe vpon an other? Now by the reaſon of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity geuen to Magiſtrates for putatiue fathers, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath béene brought in queſtion and diſgrace, and yet without cauſe of deſart; and when he hath receyued either criminall or corporall puniſhment, and hath procéeded in his purgation in Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtes for criminall cauſes, the wretched wemen afterward haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the contrary without coaction, that either they were perſwaded or hired to nominate and accuſe the innocent, thereby to excuſe and cléere the Actor from ignominy: or that they did it of pollicy to name ſuch a one as was well able by his liuing to ſatiſfie the law, or at leaſt might beare them out with leſſe rebuke then the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour. It is no maruaile <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaid, <hi>I haue found one man of a thouſand: but a woman amongſt them all I haue not found, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.30. For what will not a wicked woman in her malice imagine? How impudently did <hi>Putiphars</hi> wife forge lyes of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> becauſe he would not lye with her? <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.12. How bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did the harlot lay the death of her childe to an other, when ſhée had ouerlayne it her ſelfe? 1. <hi>King.</hi> 3.19. A whoare makes no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a lye, an oathe, or any thing ſo incredible to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14253:20"/> horrible to heare: the reaſon is becauſe (as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi>) ſaith. <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.3. <hi>ſhee hath a forehead that will not be aſhamed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is as daungerous to trauaile through a wilde forreſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fire, as to kéepe a good Name without foreſight. Let a man but frequent his friendes houſe vppon neighbourhood or neceſſary occaſions, or be but conuerſant with a woman vpon ſome honeſt intent: you ſhall haue ſome or other that (meaſuring others by their owne motions, and cenſuring others of ſuſpicion by their owne diſpoſition) wilbe ready to rayſe an ill reporte to hinder hys good Name: which being once bruted, will not be beaten downe in haſt, becauſe moſt are ready and reioyce to heare leaſinges. I confeſſe as there be too few men like <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to reſiſt the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring aſſaultes of the fleſh when they are allured: ſo there bée not many wemen that can truely ſay as <hi>Bilia</hi> did, whome <hi>S. Hierom</hi> maketh mention on. <hi>Duellius</hi> her huſband had a ſtinking breath, who being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rayded for it by one that fell out with him: he rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his wife becauſe ſhée did not tell him of it, that hée might haue found ſome remedy for it. She ſaid, ſhe would haue told him, but that ſhee thought euery mans breath ſmelled ſo: yet God defend (how few good ſoeuer there bee) any ſhould bee raſhly reproached, where there is no pretence of ill.</p>
               <p>Therefore I would wiſh euery one to avoyde the very occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of euill, if it be poſſible. <hi>Venien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> occurrite morbo,</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the worſt. <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> would neuer dwell with his ſiſter in one houſe, for he would ſay, it was inough to ſée a woman, worſe to ſpeake with her, and woorſt of all to touch her. <hi>Cato</hi> the elder baniſhed <hi>Gaius Manlius</hi> out of the Senate houſe, becauſe hee kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but his owne wife in his daughters preſence. King <hi>Hiero</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned the Poet <hi>Epicharmus,</hi> becauſe he vſed vncleanely wordes in a great ſomme of money. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> made a law that the we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Lacedemonia</hi> ſhould couer their faces when they went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, becauſe they might neither looke, nor be looked vpon. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſar</hi> commaunded no wemen ſhould come to ſée the wraſtlers, becauſe they did vſe to wraſtle naked: all theſe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſe to note how neceſſary it is to auoide the occaſion of euill for feare of inconuenience: now if the occaſion bée ſo daungerous,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14253:20"/> the very action of euill muſt néedes be deteſtable and hurtfull to the Name: for although ſome may commit ſome odious crime, and may haue it concealed for his credite, or not ſpoken of for hys cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or not regarded for hys countenaunce, or bolſtered out by fréendſhip: (for the common prouerbe is true, <hi>A mans matter is ended, as he is frended,</hi> and <hi>Some may better ſteale a horſe, then an other looke on. Modeſtinus</hi> could ſay in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tyme of Tranſgreſſors, that ſome were gréeuouſly puniſhed, others ſcarce touched. For this cauſe <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> likened the lawes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Cobwebs, which do tie little flies faſt, but breake with the great.) Yet as one kernell of <hi>Colloquintida</hi> will make the beſt br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bitter, and one deade flye will putrifie a boxe of ointment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> euill action will diſgrace many good. I will vſe one exa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſtéed of many: ſo long as <hi>Vzziah</hi> ſought the Lord, hee pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ted, and was ſo valiant, that it is ſaide, his Name ſpredd farre a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>road: but that one acte of his in vſurping the Prieſtes Office, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> defame all his former, and ſo much diminiſhed his Name, that he which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore liued as a king in his pallace at Hieruſalem, did dwell as a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par in an houſe apart. 2, <hi>Chro.</hi> 26.</p>
               <p>Although a good Name may bée recouered agayne in time: for <hi>Tempus edax rerum:</hi> Yet it wilbe long ere it bée worne out of mens mouthes and memories: Yea and when the beſt is done, as it is hard to cure a wound ſo well, but that a skarre will appeare in the skinne, ſo you ſhall as hardly recouer the other, but it wilbe a blot to the Name.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A generall application.</head>
               <p>COnſidering the excellency of a good Name ſurpaſſeth all other terreſtriall bleſſinges, there is ſpecially to bee obſerued two thinges?</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In the Speakers.</item>
                  <item>2. In the Hearers.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:14253:21"/>
               <p>THe Speakers muſt take héede how they vſe their tongues, Nature hath lent vs two eares and but one tongue, that wée might not vtter all we heare: this tongue is reared and hedged in with a double fence, to the end we might ſpeake without offence.</p>
               <p>The tongue is <hi>ianua vitae &amp; necis:</hi> it is no ſmall vertue to bridle the tongue ſaith <hi>Cato: Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee that hath a naughty tongue, ſhall fall into euill. Prou.</hi> 17.5. <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith <hi>that mans religion is in vaine, which refraineth not his tongue. S. Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>If any man long after life and to ſee good dayes, let him refraine his tongue from euill. Eſop</hi> béeing bid to buy the beſt and worſt meat in the market, brought home nothing but tongues: noting thereby, that the tonge was good and euill as it is vſed. The Pſalmiſt kept ſilence euen from ſpeaking good things, much more ought we from euill. If wée muſt giue accompt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery idle word, much more for lewd and lying ſpéeches. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt take héede how you blemiſh the Name of your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, either by carrying of Tales, <hi>Thou ſhalt not go about with tales. Leuit.</hi> 19.16. or by rayſing flaunders, <hi>He that inuenteth ſlaunder, is a foole. Prou.</hi> 10.18. Tales and ſlaunderous ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſayth <hi>Dauid,</hi> are as the ſharpe arrowes of a mighty man. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120. For as a ſtrong man ſhooteth far and doth much harme with a ſharpe arrow, ſo a ſlanderer defameth farre and doth much miſchiefe with his viperous tongue.</p>
               <p>Tales and ſlaunders are by the Pſalmograph likened to the coales of Iuniper. <hi>pſal.</hi> 120. <hi>Pliny</hi> writing of the nature thereof, ſaith, that thoſe coales doo yéeld the greateſt heat, ſo a lewd tongue doth procure the greteſt hurt. <hi>S. Iames</hi> likeneth the tongue to fire: we all know how great a thing a little fire will kindle, and ſo it is with the ſlanderer, one ſparke of ill ſpéech may cauſe a flame of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame amongſt many: for as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith nothing fléeth more ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then an ill word, nothing goeth ſooner foorth, nothing is ſooner ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor broder ſpread: it was this y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made <hi>Dauid</hi> complaine, <hi>Thou makeſt vs a reproach amongſt our neighbours &amp;c.</hi> concluding thus <hi>for the voice of the ſlaunderers. Pſal.</hi> 44. Tales and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders well impeach the beſt Name: for the moſt part are apte to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue that is ill, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h <hi>Ouid,</hi> and therefore ſayth <hi>Salomon, The
<pb facs="tcp:14253:21"/> wordes of a Talebearer are as flatteringes, and they go down into the bowels of the belly, Prou.</hi> 18.8. doe wee not ſée many times amongeſt vs, that if an ill ſpéech or tale bee vttered and bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (though but by one baſe perſon of no reputation) how ready a multitude will beléeue it? theſe are they that cauſe ſuch idle expence of money, and debate amongeſt fréendes, for who can abide to bée euill ſpoken of? therefore ſaith the wiſeman, <hi>Without a tale bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ſtrife ceaſeth. Prou.</hi> 26.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qualis vir, talis oratio.</hi> A good man is diſcerned from a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by his talke: for the godly man of loue will couer ſome offence, but the wicked of malice will exclaime without cauſe. Hereof ſaith the Scripture, <hi>A righteous man hateth lying woordes, but the wicked cauſe ſlaunder and ſhame. Pro.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A caueat for Talebearers, Backbyters and Slaunderers.</head>
               <p>THeſe men, or rather monſters amongſt men, ſhould conſider two thinges. Firſt, in their neighbour. Secondly, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>In their neighbour, they are to weigh the woorth of a good Name: which they ſhall the better performe, if they reaſon wyth themſelues by way of compariſon, thus: If it be a gréefe to a man to haue a wound in his body, what is it to haue a mayne in hys Name? for arte may cure the one, but nothing will recouer the other. If it be a gréefe for a man to looſe all his goods, which he hath béene long in gathering together, what is it to looſe his Name which he hath laboured for all his life? For one may be reſtored in time, the other is ſtayned for euer.</p>
               <p>In themſelues, they muſt weigh the reward of their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: they are abhorred both of God and Man. God deteſteth ſuch kind of men, as appéereth by many pregnant places in his woord. <hi>Him that priuily ſlaundereth his neighbour, will I deſtroy. Pſal.</hi> 101.5. <hi>the backbyter ſhall not be eſtabliſhed vpon earth Pſalm.</hi> 140.11. <hi>he that ſpeaketh lyes ſhall periſh. Prou.</hi> 19.9. The Lord puniſhed <hi>Ely</hi> and his poſterity, becauſe hys ſonnes ran into a ſlaunder, and he ſtayd them not. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. he puniſhed
<pb facs="tcp:14253:22"/> the two Iudges for ſlaundering <hi>Suſanna:</hi> the leproſſe was layd vpon <hi>Gehazi,</hi> becauſe he made a lye: and <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sapphira</hi> were puniſhed with preſent death, becauſe they made an horrible lye. <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>A godly man doth balke backbiters, ſlaunderers and ſuch like. The iuſt man ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> cannot away with a lye: much leſſe with him that vſeth it: he ſayes in an other place, that a buſie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is hated. <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.17. the Philoſophers could not abide them: therefore <hi>Pithagoras</hi> willeth vs not to receiue a ſwallow into our houſes, meaning bablers, clatterers and ſuch like companions. The <hi>Cretians</hi> were neuer accompted on, becauſe they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lyers. <hi>Moſes</hi> made a law to puniſh the ſlaunderer with loſſe of mony, for the miſdemeanor of his mouth. <hi>Deuter.</hi> 22. Now to the ſecond point.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>For Hearers.</head>
                  <p>THe Hearers muſt regard how they liſten too, and beléeue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes: for wée commonly ſay, the receiuer is as ill as the thiefe: if there were not ſo many to geue eare to lyes and beléeue them, there would not bée ſo many to deuiſe tales and tell them. Therefore the Pſalmiſt doth not onely condemne him which rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but him which receyueth a falſe report againſt his neighbour <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3. For this cauſe <hi>S. Barnard</hi> doubted whether it were a greater ſin to inuent, or liſten to a ſlander: therfore ſuch as receiue reportes and ill ſpéeches by heare ſay, muſt remember many thinges. Firſt, that if <hi>Saba</hi> would not beléeue a true report of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> till ſhee had tried out the trueth, much leſſe ought any to beléeue a falſe report of their neighbours too raſhly. Secondly, that there be ſome that take all their pleaſure to depraue others, and do nothing but inuent lies &amp; lewd ſpéeches. <hi>Thou geueſt thy mouth to euill, and with thy tongue thou forgeſt deceit, thou ſitteſt and ſpeakeſt againſt thy brother, and ſlandereſt thy mothers ſonne. Pſal.</hi> 50.19.20. Hee that will not let to ſlaunder his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſonne, ſo néere bound by nature, what wil he do to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? Theſe for the moſt part are the offſcummes of a Country: <hi>The abiectes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) aſſembled themſelues againſt mee,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14253:22"/> they tare me and ceaſed not. Pſal.</hi> 35.15. His meaning is, that the very reffuſe people did moſt rayle vppon him: and true it is, when Alewormes are quaffing on their tipling bench, then mens credites goe to wracke with theyr cuppes, and as <hi>Sampſon</hi> when hys eyes were out, did not care on whoſe head the houſe might fall, or as the Drone will hinder the Bée of her winges, when he hath loſt his owne: ſo do they ſéeke to blemiſh their betters, when themſelues are of no accompt or eſtimation. Thirdly, there bée ſome that repine at their neighbours good Names, and therefore vſe all meanes to detract it, as appéeres by <hi>Tobiah</hi> and <hi>Sanballat</hi> againſt <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and the Rulers and Gouernors againſt <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel:</hi> the examples at large are a little before: When ſuch as theſe can no way woorke their will, they wiſh the death of the godly, that ſo their Name might peariſh. <hi>Mine enemies ſpeake euill of me</hi> (ſaith <hi>Dauid) ſaying, when ſhal he die, &amp; his Name periſh. Pſal.</hi> 41.5. <hi>Saul</hi> would haue ſlayne him becauſe the people aſcribed the greater Name to him, in that <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſlaine tenne thouſand, and <hi>Saul</hi> but a thouſand. 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.8. the people of <hi>Iudah</hi> would haue deſtroyed <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that his Name might be no more in memory. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 11.19. Fourthly, you muſt reproue ſuch lewd detractors, and no way bewray any credulity, not ſo much as by a fauourable countenance: for as the Northwind dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away rayne, ſo doeth an angry countenaunce, the ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tongue, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 25.23. and if no approbation may be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by any outward apparance, much leſſe muſt you adhibite any credite to ſuch detractors: for that is an argument of impiety: hereof ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>The wicked geue heede to falſe lips, and a lier harkeneth to the naughty tongue. Prou.</hi> 17.4. Fiftly, It is the point of a wiſeman to conſider all circumſtances ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly, that touch the Name of his neighbour, and not to be too cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous: for ſuch commonly as bée light of beléefe, are ſo in theyr liues: Therefore ſayth <hi>Salomon, the fooliſh will beleeue euery thing. pro.</hi> 14.15. It is the part of a Chriſtian to doe as he would be done to: then, if you would bée loth to haue an other heare euill of your ſelfe and ſooth him, the like doe for an other. If the Apoſtle willeth that one ſhould not ſpeake euill of an other, he will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14253:23"/> one to heare euill of an other, but that the rule of charity ſhould be obſerued in both. Sixtly, it is the part of a wicked man when he heareth his neighbour ill reported of, to diſpearce it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whiſperingly, when he ſhould charitably informe him. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> complayned of this, <hi>Al they that hate me, whiſper together againſt me. Pſal.</hi> 41.7. Of ſuch kinde of whiſperers we haue too many at this day: for by this meanes, a man ſhall haue a rumor and crime raiſed of him, and yet neuer come to know either accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor or author of it: <hi>Veritas non quaerit angulos,</hi> it is the rather to be ſuſpected to be a vile enuious inuention, The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> condemneth whiſperers and inuenters of euill, as appéereth in the <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.29. Seauenthly, you muſt beware how you beléeue a Tale or ill report, though there appéere great preſumptions: all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there can bée no ſmoke without a fire, yet there may bée moſt ſmoke when there is leaſt fire: <hi>Omne ſimile non eſt idem.</hi> Violent preſumptions may induce much, as appéereth by <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in handling of two harlots: 1. <hi>king.</hi> 3.27. but as his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was extraordinary: ſo I take it to be an acte rather of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration then imitation. God forbid that euery ordinary preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould be of credite to conuince. The two Iudges deuiſed a ſuſpicious matter againſt <hi>Suſanna:</hi> yet their gréeuous puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the end doth diſcouer their egregious impiety in the acte, and her innocency from offence. <hi>Putifars</hi> wife could pull away <hi>Ioſephs</hi> garments, and tell a very ſuſpitious tale againſt him: (as the wicked care not in their malice what they imagine) but if you read the ſtory, it will appéere her tales were falſe, and ſhe in al the fault. Eightly, you muſt not altogether credite ſpéeches, though there appéere ſome proofe: for falſe witneſſe of malice may be ſuborned for mony, and men in their malice care not what wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon they vſe, ſo they may maſſacre. Our Sauiour Chriſt without ſubornation of witneſſes could neuer haue bene condemned by his aduerſaries. The Libertines and the reſt of that Synagogue could find no coulor of cauſe to ſtone <hi>Steuen,</hi> but by ſuborned witneſſes. The Elders and Nobles could neuer haue condemned <hi>Naboth</hi> but for two wicked ſuborned witneſſes. 1. <hi>king.</hi> 21.13. Therefore you muſt haue a reſpect to the reputation of the perſons, and beléeue
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14253:23"/> not euery bare and beggarly teſtimony. Ninthly, you muſt not peremptorily alwayes beléeue euery matter though ſentence bée paſſed: there be many reaſons for it: May not right by might bée ouermaſtered, as many poore men are oppreſſed when they are in ſuite with their ſuperiors, or buckle any way with their betters? May not the Poets words be verified in ſome Iudges? <hi>Sic volo, ſic iubeo, ſtat pro ratione voluntas. Wee haue a Law, and by our Law ought he to die. Iohn</hi> 19.7. May they not be corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of malice, becauſe they cannot effect their owne mindes, as the two Iudges were againſt <hi>Suſanna,</hi> becauſe they might not haue their filthy deſires on her. May they not be blinded with bribes to peruert Iudgement, as <hi>Ioel</hi> and <hi>Abiah</hi> were? 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.3. May they not be carried with letters to deale iniuriouſly, as the Elders and Nobles of Izreel were by a letter ſent from <hi>Iezebel?</hi> 1. <hi>king.</hi> 21.11. May they not deale partially either for feare of offending their frendes, as Pilot delt with Chriſt to pleaſe <hi>Ceſar, Iohn.</hi> 19 12.13. or for loue of their frendes, as <hi>Herod</hi> delt with <hi>Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> for <hi>Herodias</hi> daughters ſake? We haue many good Iudges at this day (God continue and increaſe them) but I am the more ample in this matter, becauſe we may not onely ſée what corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath béene in all ages and eſtates of perſons, but that we may perceiue how we may be deceiued in cenſuring him that hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſentence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>For Scoffers, Scorners, Mockers, and ſuch like monſters.</head>
                  <p>IT is a ſtraunge thing to note the iniquity of theſe times, if a man fall into ſome croſſe (as the beſt hath his procliuity to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uity) how ready the light and lewd people are to reproch him. <hi>Iob</hi> complained of this: <hi>Thou haſt made me a by-word of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and I am as a tabret before them, and now I am their ſong and their talke. Iob</hi> 17. When his owne frendes and kinſfolkes came to viſite him, they did nothing but vexe him. If a man were derided onely by his ennemies (yet <hi>Periander</hi> willeth to hide our miſfortune, that our ennemies reioyce not) his might the better beare it: but oftentimes ſuch as profeſſe great frendſhip and be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14253:24"/> with him, will abuſe hym behynde hys backe. <hi>Dauid</hi> had experience hereof, for he ſaith, <hi>Mine enemy did not defame me, for I could haue borne it, but it was thou O man, euen my companion, my guide and my familiar. Pſal.</hi> 55.13. <hi>Yea my familiar frend, whome I truſted, which did eate of my bread, hath lifted vp the heele againſt me. Pſalm.</hi> 41.9. <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> were godly men: yet they were ſubiect to the burthen of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquy. As the troubles of the righteous are many, ſo they are moſt ſpighted and afflicted when they fall: many prophane perſons ſhalbe countenaunced and ſupported in their faultes, be they neuer ſo criminall, as the children of <hi>Ely</hi> were, when the more reformed man ſhalbe perſecuted, and reproached in his fall, bee it neuer ſo light: but if ſo rare men as theſe, were mocked, their inferiours muſt not thincke much, although mocking and deriſion will pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate the moſt patient man. It is ſo repugnant from nature, that many more regard it, then Gods glory, as <hi>Zedekiah</hi> did. <hi>Iere.</hi> 38.19. It is ſo importable, that it is tearmed perſecuting in the Galathians: When <hi>Sara</hi> was mocked by <hi>Hagar:</hi> it is ſo intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, that the Children were deuoured by beares for mocking <hi>Eliſha.</hi> Good God, where is this vnity of brethren, and concord of Chriſtians become, when in ſtéede of loue they vſe laughter, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in ſtéede of mourning, deſpiſing in ſtéede of pitying, exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſtéede of conſolation? When <hi>Abraham</hi> the moſt religious man in the land had ſinned (whereof might haue enſued many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils) <hi>Abimelech</hi> did not twit him either by his religion, or caſt him in the téeth with his lying: but he was ſo farre from deriding him, as he pittied him, and ſo far from hurting him, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed many preſents vpon him: this heathen king will condemne many Chriſtians at this day. When the Iewes brought the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultereſſe woman before our Sauiour Chriſt, he was ſo far from vpbrayding her for her fault: that he reproued them for reioycinge in her fall: He bode him that was frée from ſinne, to throw the firſt ſtone, and her to depart and ſinne no more. <hi>Triſtitia diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit cor,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine:</hi> trouble ſtrikes a terror into the mind of a good man, and is ſorrow inough of it ſelfe, without this miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable torment of mocking: and therefore we ought to comfort and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14253:24"/> not croſſe ſuch as be corrigible in their fall, but to be fellow-fée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling members in their afflictions: <hi>Paul</hi> willeth the Romaines to wéepe with thoſe that wéepe, and <hi>Iob</hi> ſayth, <hi>Did not I weepe with him that is in trouble? Iob.</hi> 30.25. What if thy brother offend of infirmity? is hée the firſt, or like to bée the laſt? or art thou thy ſelfe frée, or maiſt thou not fall? conſider thy owne caſe, and thou ſhalt haue ſmall reaſon to bee rigorous to an other. If we ſinne all in many thinges, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.2. art not thou culpable in ſome thinge? then rather take warning by an other, then won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at him. Is his ſinne made notorious by the malice of enemies, and thine concealed by the meanes of frendes, or had in ſuſpition or ſpéech by many violent preſumptions? <hi>Si non caſtè, tamen cautè:</hi> or haſt thou not ſomeway deſerued reproach by thy life, though it be not brought to light? howſoeuer it be, ſay the beſt of thy brother without ſcoffing or ſcorning, leaſt he from whome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is hid, doth bewray thy ſinnes to thy ſhame. There are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of miſdoers: ſome are but touched, others taineted wyth notorious crimes (although taineting is not common to euery tranſgreſſor) many ſinnes are priuate, others more publike: yet we ought to haue this reſpect, that we meaſure ſome not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quality of his offence, but the diſpoſition of the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor: therefore ſaith <hi>Iude, Haue compaſsion of ſome puttinge difference Iud.</hi> 22. and becauſe the penitent ought to be pitied <hi>S. Paul</hi> willeth the Galathians to reſtore ſuch as haue fallen by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion into a fault, and leaſt any ſhould inſult and reioyce at hys fall, he put in this <hi>memento</hi> by the way, as a perfect reaſon drawn from humane imperfection, <hi>Leaſt thy ſelfe be tempted. Gal.</hi> 6.1. What ſhould moue thée to deride thy brother when he falleth? Doeſt thou take him for an abiect? then I accompt thée a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate: for the beſt that euer were (being but men) haue fallen: Search throughout the whole courſe of Scriptures, and how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall you finde, that were euer ſo high for theyr calling, ſo holy for their conuerſation, ſo renowned in Name: that haue not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded either priuately or publikely. If thy brother riſe by repentance, as his predeceſſors haue done, why ſhouldeſt thou thinke hys fall more infamous then theirs, or his ſoule leſſe pretious then thine,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14253:25"/> ſéeing whome God croſſeth here, he crowneth in heauen? What ſhould make thée diſdayne the company of thy brother when hée falleth? Is it thy integrity? If thou ſtandeſt, remember <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell to the Corinthians: <hi>Take heede thou doeſt not fall:</hi> yet thy contempt cannot excuſe, but rather accuſe thée of euill: for thoſe which did ſay, <hi>Stand apart come not neere mee, I am ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier then thou, Eſay</hi> 65.5. they were no better then hypocrites, and ſo maiſt thou bée: but ſay thou art as cléere from ſinne as Chriſt, yet take enſample by thy Sauiour: for he diſdained not the company of Publicans and Sinners, which in thoſe dayes the Iewes accompted the very ofſcummes of the earth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A very ſpeciall Note.</head>
               <p>HE that wilbe ſtrickt in reproouing, muſt not be ſtayned in his liuing: for <hi>Tully</hi> ſaith, it is the property of a foole to ſpie faults in other and forget his owne. He that doth regiſter others eſcapes, ſhould not be rechleſſe himſelfe: and to twit one by that which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or his haue bene toucht withall, is a méere point of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency. With what force canſt thou vtter in diſgrace of thy peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent brother: <hi>There goes a drunkard,</hi> when many can tell thée, thou haſt beene ouertaken with drinke? With what boldneſſe canſt thou ſay: <hi>There iets a proud perſon,</hi> when thy gate, geſture and gouernement, are great preſumptions of pride? With what credite maiſt thou report, <hi>There goes an Adulterer,</hi> when thou thy ſelfe art accompted an incontinent liuer? With what coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance canſt thou ſay, <hi>There goes an Vſurer</hi> (which takes but tenne in the hundred for mony) when thou takeſt after thirty in the hundred in thy trade? With what ſhame maiſt thou publiſh, <hi>There goes a blaſphemer,</hi> when thou thy ſelfe haſt béene tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with hereticall blaſphemy? I ſpeake not to the mainetenance of any obſtinate and vncorrigible ſinner, but to croſſe theſe cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſpirites, which ſpend their mouthes in ſpighte againſt others, when their owne woorkes may accuſe them of vanity in their wordes. The Apoſtle doth not exclude them, when hee reprooueth him that ſpeakes againſt ſtealing, &amp; yet playes the thiefe? <hi>Ro.</hi> 2.21.
<pb facs="tcp:14253:25"/> It is not inuaighing ſpéech can varniſh a vitious man, nor a hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> looke can couer a diſhoneſt life, nor a braſen face can hide a bad fact: but he that reſpecteth no perſon but his piety, no titles but integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no excuſe but ſimplicity, will not onely reueale ſuch as be euill, but reuenge it here or in the world to come. Some will obiect, they haue not fallen into the like offence their brother haue: what then? hath he ſinned by incontinency? you by couetouſnes: he in pride? you by oppreſſion: hée by bribing? you by blaſpheming: hée one way? you an other: yet ye be both liable to a like verdite: for hée that ſayes the one ſhall not come in heauen, will not ſuffer the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to inherite without repentance. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some are croſſed with loſſe of their goods, as <hi>Iob</hi> was: many with vntoward children, as <hi>Eli</hi> was: and with death of their children, as the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Sarepta</hi> was: others with diſeaſes of body, as <hi>Naomi</hi> was with leproſie, ſome with loſſe of their Name, as <hi>Cain</hi> was, who liued to his reproach: although God doth not infli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t theſe in like manner and meaſure to all, yet ſithence few or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are frée from theſe afflictions, one ought not to applaud in an others miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: <hi>For he that reioyceth at deſtruction, ſhall not go vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon Prou.</hi> 17.5. Euery one ſhould ſquare his ſpéech by the rule of charity, &amp; waigh his deſartes in the ballance of equity, &amp; then he ſhall find, that if his owne faults were branded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his forehead, he ſhall hardly eſcape without a blemiſh on his face, if he pull not his hat ſomewhat low ouer his browes. <hi>Sibi quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> proximus,</hi> euery man can looke forward to his neighbours faults, but hath not an eye to his owne, ſuch as theſe can ſtraine a gnatt but ſwallow a camell, ſtomble at a ſtraw, but leape ouer a blocke like hypocriticall Iewes, who could tith minte, but ouer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ip great matters. If ſome of them did examine and compare their owne actions with others, they might ſay as <hi>Iudah</hi> did of <hi>Tamar, She is more righteous then I. Gen.</hi> 28. and many of them may offer ſacrifice euery day with <hi>Iob</hi> for their vitious and volupt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: they may heare many ill reportes of them, as <hi>Eli</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his ſonnes, but they can ſuffer th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m to procéede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n without puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when an other ſhalbe perſecuted in the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt trip of his life.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb facs="tcp:14253:26"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Eaſt he that hath a good Name ſhould be too glorious, or he that hath an ill Name, ſhould be too much diſgra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced, I thought good to ad this concluſiue caueat by the way. A good Name although it be excellent, yet it is earthly: though it be memorable, yet it is momentany: though it be committed to Rolles of record by Chronologiers, or engrauen in braſſe as they vſe in ſome countrey, yet both the Actors wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges and all will weare away in time: the Philoſopher could ſay <hi>Quàm multos clariſsimos ſuis temporibus viros ſcripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inops deleuet obliuio?</hi> Such as be experienced by age can tell, how many men that in their time were noble and famous, be now cleane forgotten and out of memory. Whereby we may ſée the fraile fruition of euery temporary thing, which is ſoone decided with the circle of time, ſo that no perpetuity in this life can be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of the moſt pretious thing. A good Name: therfore we muſt not labour or looke to eternize our Names vpon earth, but rather couet and craue that we may be in the nomber of thoſe whoſe Names are written in heauen: for as the Lord ſayth in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay,</hi> that is an euerlaſting Name which ſhall not be put out <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.5. and albeit many ſhall haue their Names blemiſhed in this life, bleſſed are they if they be not blotted out of the boke of life.</p>
               <p>The Marchant will barter his reffuſe ware with hys beſt, the Vintner will draw his decayed wine with his better. If thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of infirmity fall, <hi>actiones cum fama expendito,</hi> thou art to conſider not onely the offence which procured il report, but by how many other actions he is worthy praiſe, and ſo balla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce one againſt an other, for this courſe is commonly vſed in the Scriptures. You ſhall find <hi>Abrahams</hi> folly to be recorded aſwel as his faith, <hi>Noahs</hi> ebriety aſwell as his integrity, <hi>Salomons</hi> wantonneſſe aſwel as his wiſdome, <hi>Pauls</hi> perſecuting aſwell as his preaching, <hi>Peters</hi> periury aſwell as his penitency: yet their eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll factes be not applied to their infamy but infirmity, neither be their Names extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed but eternized.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:14253:26"/>
               <p>If Princes, Patriarkes, Prophets and Apoſtles haue their faultes, meruaile not ſo much at their inferiors if they fall: and therefore as we terme not that trée to be ill, which is many times blaſted, ſo it beareth good fruite to the end: ſo we muſt not take that man to be infamous, which many times falleth, ſo he riſeth by repentance to his death.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="aphorisms">
            <head>Certaine pithy and profitable Apothegues, directing men to thriue, not ſo much by their goods as gouernement.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lambe is by the Lyon, there is no feare of the Wolfe. He that is ſhrouded vnder his ſuperior, is in leſſe daunger of diſpleaſure: for he ſhalbe ſometime ſpared, when others are ſpighted, many waies pittied when others are oppreſſed. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> could neuer be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>et, vntill he had got in fauour vnder <hi>Pharaoh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſpundge wil be full of water and not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne: If thou haſt <hi>ſatis,</hi> inſult not, leaſt thou be plagued with <hi>non putaram:</hi> for we are here in this world among men, as in a wilderneſſe among beaſtes, not ſo ready to turne any away as to be torne. He that hath <hi>Creſſus</hi> wealth, had néede haue <hi>Argus</hi> eyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The leaking veſſell will hold no lyquor, nor the riotous man any liuing: for whole mines will not mainetaine a prodigall mind. It is better to ſpare with a care of increaſing, then to ſpende without cauſe in conſuming. The Prodigall ſonne by hys great ryot came to ruine.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That lampe is beſt that kéepeth light longeſt. He that will come to preferment, muſt keepe hys patrimony: for wée ſée the courſe of the world, that riches bring many to renowne, when po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty maketh any of no accompt. <hi>Naboth</hi> would in no wiſe depart from his inheritance.</p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, if thou wilt liue after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be poore: if after thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. True it is, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Alexander</hi> are not fit for <hi>Codrus,</hi> it is good to be frugall in our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14253:27"/> fare: for he that loueth banqueting, ſhall ſooneſt die a beggar. Chriſt was content with broyled fiſh, then order your diet by him that died for you.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The ſhéepe yéeldeth her fléece to defend vs from cold, not to inflate vs with pride. Let euery one cut his coat according to hys cloth: for the end of brauery is beggary. <hi>Adams</hi> loynes were but clad with leather: then let your new faſhions take patterne of your firſt father.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Our forefathers vſed no other drincke but water from the creation vntill the inundation of the world. Vſe wine more for weakeneſſe then wantonneſſe: for it is not made to confound the wits, but to comfort the memory, not to inflame the liuer, but to refreſh the hart. <hi>Timothy</hi> by taking of a little wine preſerued his health.</p>
            <p n="8">8 One demaunded of <hi>Diogenes</hi> when it was beſt to marry: for a young man (quoth he) it is too ſoone, for an old man ouerlate: His aunſweare is good: for to marry, it is too ſoone without main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and to tarry, it is a ſinne without chaſtity. Hée that will pleaſe his eye for loue, muſt not impaire his eſtate for liuing. <hi>Iaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> had gathered liuinge vnder <hi>Laban,</hi> before hee married hys daughters.</p>
            <p n="9">9 <hi>Demea</hi> in <hi>Terence</hi> ſayth, I haue married a wife: what miſery haue I ſéene therein? Haue reſpect to your choyce, leaſt your marriage bréed your miſery. It is a gréefe to a good man, to be troubled with a ſcold, like <hi>Socrates,</hi> when hée would bée quiet: or with a deuill like <hi>Iob,</hi> when he is in diſtreſſe: or with a whore like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> when he bewrayes his ſecretes.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Eſchew the company of Curtiſans: for their bodies are made of Adamant to draw their eyes of Eaſiliſke to blinde their wordes of Syrens to inchaunt: as <hi>Salomons</hi> wiſedome was firſt tried by whores, ſo his ouerthrow was at laſt wroght by whores.</p>
            <p n="11">11 He that hath béene ſinged in the flame will take héede of the fire: he that will be ſure muſt hate ſuertyſhip, an honeſt denial may ſatiſfie an hurtfull demaund, yet thou art bound to benefite thy brother, ſo thy duety be vſed with diſcretion. <hi>Syrach</hi> ſaith, <hi>an honeſt man is ſuerty for his neighbour.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:14253:27"/>
            <p n="12">12 Lend to thy better for a benefite, but to the poore for a bleſſing: ſhe one borrowes to encreaſe hys wealth: the other to ſupply his want. In all thy actions be circumſpect: for ſimple dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is ſooneſt vndone without foreſight. Truſt not woordes: for <hi>Laban</hi> deceiued <hi>Iaacob</hi> with faire wordes, but take a pledge: for <hi>Tamar</hi> would not truſt <hi>Iudah</hi> for a trifle without a pledge: or els take ſome ſpecialty: for <hi>Gabael</hi> had the handwriting of <hi>Raphael</hi> when he receiued mony.</p>
            <p n="13">13 Shake not thy head when thou ſhouldſt ſtretch foorth thy hand to the poore, like churles who commonly giue anod, when they meane to giue nothing: the poore are the Altars to lay the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of our goods. <hi>Cornelius</hi> almes came into remembrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p n="14">14 The ſpanyell neuer fawneth but he wage his taile. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can pleaſantly perſonate with faire ſpéech, <hi>O my good freend &amp;c.</hi> and ſhake one by the fifte. But as the liquorice leaſe l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth moſt dry when it is moſt moiſt: ſo theſe doo meane moſt deceipte, when they ſéeme moſt merry. <hi>Cain</hi> was very kind in ſpéech when he ment to kill <hi>Abel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15 He that toucheth pitch ſhalbe defiled: Conuerſe with the godly, ſo it may be for thy good: for the wicked being ſociable with them, ſpéede the better for their ſakes: <hi>Laban</hi> proſpered the better for <hi>Iaacob,</hi> and <hi>Putiphar</hi> for <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> when <hi>Dauid</hi> directed the bandes, <hi>Saul</hi> had good ſucceſſe in his battailes.</p>
            <p n="16">16 The higheſt Towers are moſt ſubiect to tempeſtes, a cottage with contentment is better then a pallace wyth controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: wiſedome conſiſteth not in wealth, but in contempt of the world, nor wealth in aboundance, but in content of the minde. <hi>Diogenes</hi> did better eſtéeme of his tub, then <hi>Alexander</hi> of all his treaſure.</p>
            <p n="17">17 Timely prickes the trée that will prooue a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d thorne. Take thy eaſe according to thy eſtate, if thou béeſt poore, put thy paines to Gods prouidence: for his bleſſing maketh riche. <hi>Iacob</hi> carried nothing ouer <hi>Iordan</hi> but his ſtaffe, but he retourned rich. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was an abiect of his brethren, but he became a gouernour in <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14253:28"/>
            <p n="18">18 Let thy neighbour be thy war of man and not the law: for he that will contend for euery trifle, ſhall make the Lawyer rich with his ſiluer, and himſelfe poore by his ſuites. <hi>Abraham</hi> had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſigne his right, then be at variance with <hi>Lot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19 Vſe ſome exerciſe more to prolong thy health, then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy hinderance: avoid play, for it is a priuy thiefe to thy thrift. Thereof procéedes for the moſt part loſſe of time with treaſure, cauſe of care with curſing, breach of credite amongſt men, and ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh of conſcience before God. <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee that loueth paſtime ſhalbe poore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20 Let the Cooke be thy Phiſition, and the garden thy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary: for he that will to phiſicke for euery infirmity, ſhalbe ſure to haue his body neuer without maladies, and hys purſe euer without mony. Yet we muſt not neglect the meanes for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of health. If <hi>Aſa</hi> had depended moſt vpon God, he ſhould not haue béene reprooued for ſéeking to Phiſitions.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Store is no ſore, plenty ought to bee dainety, make no waſt of that which an other doth want: for there is nothing may ſéeme at any time ſo impure, but at ſometime may bee thought precious. <hi>Alexander</hi> thought the puddle moſt pleaſant in hys thirſt, and the Prodigall ſonne thought the ſwines huſkes m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt dainety in his hunger.</p>
            <p n="22">22 The bird will nurriſh her broode till they can flye, ſo m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt parents their children, till they be able to ſhifte. A good Science is farre better then an Inheritance: he that hath no wealth to leaue them, may do little if he teach them not ſome trade to liue on. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> reportes that <hi>Solon</hi> made a law in <hi>Athens,</hi> that the childe ſhould not be bound to ſuccour his father, of whome he had recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no manner of doctrine to liue by.</p>
            <p n="23">23 The little hare hath his ſhadow, and the ſimpleſt man his ſoule. Let not the better contemne the baſer. Call not the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman clowne: for tillage is of moſt antiquity, or the ſheapherd d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt: for ſhéepekéeping was moſt vſuall wyth our aunceſters. <hi>Noah</hi> was a huſbandman and yet a Patriarke, <hi>Dauid</hi> a ſheape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, and yet a Prince.</p>
            <p n="24">24 Auoyde idleneſſe as the nurſe of all euill. <hi>Antonine</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:14253:28"/> Emperor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> theyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that there was nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> then ſuch to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deuour the weale publike, which with their labor nothing increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it. The Romanes durſt neuer goe abroad without a badge of their occupation.</p>
            <p n="25">25 It is good to beare alowſayle in a high winde, in proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be not proud. It is beſt to caſt a ſtrong ancre in a great ſtorme, in pouerty be not impatient, it is better to liue here in miſery then to die without mercy. Whatſoeuer you ayme at, haue an eye to the end: then you ſhalbe ſure, though you liue wyth gréefe, you ſhall die with glory, and be ſaued by grace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
